<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sacke of Roome exsequuted by the Emperour Charles armie euen at the natiuitie of this Spanish Kinge Philip. Notablie described in a Spanish dialogue, with all the horrible accidents of this sacke, and abhominable sinnes, superstitions &amp; diseases of that cittie, which prouoked these iust iudgements of God. Translated latelie into the English tounge, neuer fitter to bee read nor deeplier considered, then euen now at this present time.</title>
            <title>Diálogo en que particularmente se tratan las cosas acaecidas en Roma el año de M.D.XXVII. English</title>
            <author>Valdés, Alfonso de, d. 1532.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 199 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14254</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24569</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101792</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837595</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837595</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1927</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14254)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1927)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1012:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sacke of Roome exsequuted by the Emperour Charles armie euen at the natiuitie of this Spanish Kinge Philip. Notablie described in a Spanish dialogue, with all the horrible accidents of this sacke, and abhominable sinnes, superstitions &amp; diseases of that cittie, which prouoked these iust iudgements of God. Translated latelie into the English tounge, neuer fitter to bee read nor deeplier considered, then euen now at this present time.</title>
                  <title>Diálogo en que particularmente se tratan las cosas acaecidas en Roma el año de M.D.XXVII. English</title>
                  <author>Valdés, Alfonso de, d. 1532.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[78] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Abell Ieffes for Roger Ward,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of Alfonso de Valdés.  Diálogo en que particularmente se tratan las cosas acaecidas en Roma el Año de M.D.XXVII.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K⁴ (-K4, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rome (Italy) --  History --  Siege, 1527 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1927:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1927:1"/>
            <p>THE SACKE of Roome, Exſequuted by the Emperour Charles armie euen at the Natiuitie of this Spaniſh Kinge <hi>Philip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>NOTABLIE DESCRIBED IN A</hi> Spaniſh Dialogue, with all the Horrible <hi>accidents of this Sacke, and abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſinnes, ſuperſtitions &amp; diſeaſes of that Cittie, which prouoked theſe iust iudgements of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Translated latelie into the English tounge, neuer fitter to bee read nor deeplier conſidered, then euen <hi>now at this preſent time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by Abell Ieffes <hi>for Roger Ward</hi> 1590.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translators_dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1927:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1927:2"/>
            <head>The Translator of this Spanish Dialogue <hi>to his Honeſt louing learned Friend</hi> A. V.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing in ſome publique imploime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts not long ſince ſo ouertoyled my ſelfe, as I found my liberty of returne to my former delectable ſtudies and recreations, a very Paradize in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Hel of Enuy and Mallice wherein I had beene long iniuriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with many ſtormes turmoiled: among other hiſtories and pleaſant diſcourſes that at idleſt times I read for recreation, this Spaniſh Dialogue receiued from you, ſo pleaſed me, as partlie for exerciſe of that toong, but chieflie for the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar good liking I had of the matter, and to paſſe ouer ſome melancolye conceipts (wherinto the ingratitude of ſome perſons, at whoſe handes I had but to well deſerued, had throwne me) I began to tranſlate the ſame into Engliſh, following as nigh as I could the verie Spaniſh letter, ſauing in ſuch phraſes as in our toong haue neyther grace nor ſence.</p>
            <p>The Treatiſe ſurelie is ſuch, as being read of our nation, could not but worke ſingular good effects, euen in our moſt obſtinate moderne peruerſe Papiſts, ſeeing it ſo pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pablie reuealeth the horrible errors and abuſes of that their corrupted Romane religion, or rather putrified ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition (moſt vniuſtlie by them miſnamed Catholike or Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall) and that by a couple of their owne Spaniſh partie: notſomuch by ſcriptures ſacred, where vnto they generally beare ſo ſmall reuerence, as by euident demonſtrations &amp; ſuch inuincible reaſons as were able to reduce very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens and Paynims to a better ſence: and the Method and ſtile ſuch, as if I could deliuer it in Engliſh with that grace it
<pb facs="tcp:1927:3"/> hath in the Spaniſh, were no leſſe delectable then profitable and not vnfit for other due reſpects to be printed and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed euen in this our time: that as euen at the natiuitie of this aſpiring <hi>Philip</hi> King of Spaine, their cheefe Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, Almightie God miraculouſlie ſtirred vp a little armie of their owne religion, iuſtlie to chaſtice the hatefull pride of that Babilonicall Sea, when her treacherie was not growne to that heigth of helliſh wickedneſſe, it hath ſince aſpired: So the memorie thereof reuiued by the due conſideration of euery perticuler accident, cauſe, and circumſtance, ſo wittily diſcuſſed and liuely repreſented in this diſcourſe, (conferred with the horrible treaſons and villanies in this age, before our eyes committed by that Sea, euer ſithence hatching continually new rebellions of ſubiects, murthers of annointed Kings and Princes, Maſſacres of Chriſtian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, deſtruction and ſubuerſion of kingdomes, &amp; common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weales, tending finallie to the vtter diſpeopling &amp; deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all Chriſtendome, being mounted euen to the heigth of her impietie, and ripe for ruine) may nowe likewiſe ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate &amp; ſtir vp againe ſome noble ſpirits of our time before or at the death of the ſame <hi>Phillip</hi> their chiefe Abbettour,<note place="margin">Inſtat Clima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctericus eius &amp; babilonica Clades.</note> and mainteiner, to attempt and atchieue the like, or a more glorious godly honourable enterpriſe, cauſing all men of right ſence, no leſſe to abhorre theſe diueliſh practiſes and practiſers, then their damnable wickedneſſe indeed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues: the which my traduction now finiſhed, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend to your correction and diſpoſition: and ſo leaue you to your Theologicall or Metaphyſicall muſes, and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full protection of the Almightie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:1927:3"/>
            <head>The Authors preface to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O great is the blindneſſe wherein for the moſt part the world is now drowned, that I maruell not at the falſe iudgements by the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple conceiued of this late accident of Rome: for as they ſuppoſe Religion to conſiſt onelie in theſe externall things: ſo ſeeing them ſo badlie hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, they thinke the faith to be vtterlie ouerthrowne, and in truthe as I cannot but commend, the holy zeale wherewith the common ſorte are thereto mooued, ſo can I not allowe of their ſilence, whoſe dutie were to reduce them from that error. Seeing then on the one part, how preiudiciall it ſhould be, first to the glory of God, then to the ſaluation of his people: and alſo to the honour of this most Chriſtian king and Emperour whome God hath giuen vnto vs, if theſe matters ſhould remaine thus cloaked, I haue attempted (ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther led therevnto by ſimplicitie and hartie loue, then by fooliſh arrogancie to accompliſh with this ſmall ſeruice, theſe three prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall things wherevnto men are bound. I was not ignorant that the matter was much more high and difficile then the meaſure of my forces, and yet I knowe aſwell that where there is a good inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Ieſu Christ dooth lighten the vnderſtanding, and ſupplie with his grace the defect of our forces and knowledge attained by humaine wit, My thought alſo, I did ſee repreſented before mee the falſe iudgements that ſuperſtitious Pharizes are like to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue of this matter, wherefore let them knowe, that I write not for them nor to them, but to the true Chriſtians &amp; faithfull louers of Chriſt Ieſu. Aſwell did I alſo ſee, the peruerſe contrarieties of the common ſorte, the which are ſo ſetled on things viſible, as they do almoſt make a ieſt of the things inuiſible. Remembring therfore that I wrote not to Gentiles but vnto Chriſtians, whoſe perfection is to withdraw it ſelfe from things viſible, &amp; to loue the inuiſible:
<pb facs="tcp:1927:4"/> I remembred alſo that I wrote not vnto brute people, but vnto <hi>Spaniards,</hi> whoſe wits, there is nothing ſo difficult but they are able to attaine: and ſeeing my deſires are no others then my words expreſſe, I eaſilie perſwade my ſelfe that I ſhall attaine of all that are diſcreete, and not counterfeit Chriſtians, if anie default be found in this dialogue, to interpreat the ſame in the best ſence: and impute the blame to my ignorance, and not preſume to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that mallice hath any parte therein, ſince in all I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my ſelfe to the correction and iudgement of the holy Churche, the which I acknowledge for the mother of the Diſciples of the trueth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:1927:4"/>
            <head>The firſt part of the Sacke <hi>of Rome.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <head>The Argument.</head>
               <p>A yong knight of the Emperours Court named <hi>Lattantio,</hi> met in the market place of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aledolid</hi> with an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon that came from Rome in a Souldiers habit, &amp; entring into <hi>S. Frauncis</hi> Church had communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concerning matters chaunced at <hi>Rome.</hi> In the firſt part <hi>Lattantio</hi> ſhewed the <hi>Archdeacon</hi> how the Emperour was in no fault for that matter. And in the ſecond, how God permitted all that was done for the good of Chriſtendome.</p>
            </argument>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lattantio.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Lord is not this the Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con of <hi>Viſo,</hi> the greateſt friend I had in <hi>Rome,</hi> a ſtrange matter, it ſeemes to be he, though not by his apparell, it may bee ſome brother of his: I wil not paſſe by without ſpeaking who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he bee. Tell me Gentleman, are you a brother to the Archdeacon of <hi>Viſo?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>What <hi>Segnior Lattantio</hi> haue you ſo ſoone forgotten mee? it appeares Fortune quickly chaungeth mens knowledge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>What ſay you? now I ſee you are the Archdeacon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe indeede.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yea ſir to do you ſeruice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Who could know you comming as now you do? you were woont to weare your garmentes one longer then another, trailing on the ground, your cappe after the Eccleſiaſticall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb facs="tcp:1927:5"/> your ſeruants, and reuerend Mule, but now I ſee you on foot alone, a ſhort cote, with a thred bare Friſado cape, a great ſword, and a Souldiers hat: beſides all this a long beard, and your haire and head without any ſigne of Crowne, who could haue knowen you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Who ſir? Euen he that knowes the habit by the man, and not the man by the habit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Well, if the memorie haue erred, it is no reaſon good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will ſhould paie for that fault which in me hath verie ſeldom di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed: But tell mee as God helpe you ſir, how comes this chaunge?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>What, haue you not heard what hath happened at <hi>Rome</hi> lately?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, I haue heard ſome thing, but what concernes the buſines of <hi>Rome,</hi> the chaunge of your garmentes</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Seeing you aſke that queſtion it appeares you know not al, for then you ſhould haue knowen that ther is not in <hi>Rome</hi> a man that dare paſſe the ſtreets in habit of an Eccleſiaſtical per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>What tell you mee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>I tell you that when I came from <hi>Rome,</hi> the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quution againſt the Clergie was ſo great, that there was not a man that durſt walke the ſtreetes in habit of a Clarke or a Frier.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>O merueilous God how incomprehenſible are thy Iudgements? But ſir I pray you were you within <hi>Rome</hi> at that time, when the Emperours armie entred?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yea for my ſinnes I was found or rather loſt there, for of all that euer I had I haue nothing left but that you ſee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Wherfore did you not commit your ſelfe to the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſouldiours, and thereby haue ſaued your goods.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>My ſinnes daunted my wittes, and my vnhappie lot was to fall among the <hi>Almans,</hi> where I thought it no little gaine to eſcape with life out of their handes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Is all true wee heare from thence, and that men report here?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>I know not what you heare, nor what you ſay of it, but I can aſſure you it was the moſt terrible thing that euer man ſaw, I know not how you take it here, it ſeemes to mee you make no great accompt of it. But on my ſoule I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:1927:5"/> God will ſo diſſemble it: and if wee were in ſome other place where it were lawfull for me to ſpeake I would vtter foule and terrible matters with this mouth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Againſt whom?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Againſt him that hath done more miſchiefe againſt the Church of God then euer Turke or Pagan durſt haue done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>But ſoft ſir <hi>Archdeacon,</hi> it may be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you are deceaued and lay the fault wher it is not, between vs any thing may paſſe, tell me therefore franckly your minde, and I will ſo endeuour to open vnto you your error, that you ſhall not blame him that is not blame worthie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>I am content to open plainly vnto you my mind in this matter, but not here in the Market place, let vs goe into this Church of <hi>S. Frauncis,</hi> and there we wil diſcourſe at our leiſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Agreed, let it be ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Now that we are where we may talke, and none heare vs, I pray you ſir whatſoeuer paſſeth betweene vs, let no other man be priuie of it, for Princes are Princes, and no wiſedome for men to put themſelues in perill where they neede not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Hereof you may be well aſſured.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Let vs then ſee <hi>Signior Lattantio,</hi> doth it ſeeme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you a matter tollerable that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour hath done in <hi>Rome</hi> that which neuer Infidels had done, and that for his perticuler paſſion, and to reuenge himſelfe of I wat not what, hath in ſuch ſort ſought to diſtroy the Sea Apoſtolique, with the greateſt Ignominie, and with greater Contempt, and greater crueltie than euer was heard or ſeene. I know that the <hi>Gothes</hi> tooke <hi>Rome,</hi> but yet they medled not with the Church of <hi>S. Peeter,</hi> they medled not with the Reliques of the Sainctes, they medled not with the ſacred and holie thinges. But whereas thoſe halfe Chriſtians had this reſpect, now our Chriſtians (albeit I know not whether they bee worthie of that name) they haue not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne Churches, they haue not forborne Monaſteries, they haue not forborne the ſacred thinges, they haue violated all, they haue robbed all, they haue profaned all, that I wonder the earth hath not opened and ſwallowed them vp, &amp; thoſe alſo that ſent them, or conſented vnto it. What thinke yee now will the <hi>Turkes,</hi> the <hi>Moores,</hi> the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and the <hi>Lutherans</hi> ſay, ſeeing the head of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church thus handled. O God, that ſuffreſt ſuch a thing. Oh
<pb facs="tcp:1927:6"/> God that conſenteſt to ſo great a wickednes: Was this the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtolike Sea hoped from hir defendor? was this the honor that Spaine hoped for of hir ſo mightie king? was this the glorie? was this the good? was this the Amplification and enlargement that all Chriſtendome hoped? was it for this that his great Graundfathers got the title of <hi>Catholicke?</hi> For this cauſe did they ioyne ſo many Kingdomes and Seignories vnto the rule of one Lord? for this was hee elected Emperour? for this did the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> helpe him to thruſt out the French out of Italie? To the end that in one day he ſhould deſtroy al that their predeceſſors with ſo great trauels, and in ſuch a multitude of years had founded? So many and ſuch goodly churches, ſuch Monaſteries, ſuch Hoſpitals, and Chappels, where God was woont to bee ſerued and honoured, to be now defaced and profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. So manie Altars, yea euen in the Church of the Prince of the Apoſtles embrued with bloud, ſo many Reliques robbed and with ſacrilegious handes profaned? For this cauſe did their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors adioine ſo great holineſſe to this cittie? For this did they honor the Church with ſuch and ſo many reliques? For this did they beſtow on them ſo many ritch ornamentes of Gold and Siluer? that in the end hee ſhould come without remorſe to rob, deface and deſtroy al? Oh Soueraigne God, is it poſſible that ſo great a crueltie, ſo great an outrage, ſo abhominable boldnes, ſo horrible an accident, and ſo execrable a wickedneſſe can paſſe without ſome moſt rigorous, moſt grieuous, and moſt notorious puniſhment: I know not what feeling you haue here of it, or if you haue any I merueile how ye can let it paſſe or diſſemble it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>I heare attentiuely all that you haue ſaid, and in truth albeit I heare the like vttered of that matter by manie, yet mee thinkes you make it more foule, and blame it more then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and in all that you haue ſpoken it ſeems to me you are very ill enformed, and in my iudgement it is not reaſon, but paſſion, for that you haue loſt, that cauſeth you to vtter the ſame which you haue ſpoken, I wil not ſpeake paſſionately as you haue done, for ſo ſhould we ſpend ſpeech without any Frute. But without affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionate ſpeeches, I hope truſting in your diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; good iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that before you part from me you ſhall plainlie vnderſtand how much you haue bin deceaued in all that you haue yet ſaied, onely I requeſt you to be attentiue, and not to forbeare to replie
<pb facs="tcp:1927:6"/> when you ſee cauſe, to the end you may not reſt in any doubt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Say what you wil, but I wil hold you for a greater O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator then <hi>Tullius</hi> if you be able to defend this cauſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Nay I am content you ſhal accompt me the verieſt idiot that is in the whole world if I defend it not and prooue my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to you with moſt cleere and euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t reaſons. And the firſt thing I will prooue ſhall bee how the Emperoure was in no fauit for that which happened at <hi>Rome.</hi> And ſecondly how all that happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ther came to paſſe by the manifeſt &amp; iuſt iudgement of God, to correct and chaſtice that Citie, wherein (to the great ſlaunder of Chriſtian Religion) raigned al thoſe vices that the wickednes of man could inuent, and with that correction to awake the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian people, to the end that thoſe euils being remedied we might open our eies and liue like Chriſtians, ſeeing wee glorie ſo much in that name.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>A great enterpriſe you haue taken in hand, but how you wil goe through with it I ſee not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Concerning the firſt I muſt proteſt vnto you, that no one thing of that which hereafter ſhal be ſaid is by mee ſpoken in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice of the dignitie or perſon of the Pope: For it is great reaſon that his dignitie be reuerenced of all men, and touching his owne perſon, ſurely I can ſpeake no ill if I would. Beſides that, it is well knowen that all which hee hath done hath not paſſed by his owne meanes, but by meanes of the lewdneſſe of ſome perſons y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he keepes about him. And to the end that we the better vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d one another, ſeeing this difference is betweene the Pope and the Emperour, I pray you firſt declare vnto me, what office that of the Popes is, and likewiſe what is the office of the Emperour, and to what ende or purpoſe theſe Dignities were firſt eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>It ſeemeth vnto me that the office or dutie of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour is to defende his Subiectes and to maintaine them in great Peace and Iuſtice fauouring the good, and chaſtiſing the ill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay well, but what is then that of the Pope.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>That is more hard to declare, for if wee behold the time of <hi>S. Peter,</hi> it is one, and in theſe daies another.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>But when I demaunde of you to what ende theſe digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were ordeined, it is ment that you ſhould declare vnto mee,
<pb facs="tcp:1927:7"/> their intention that did ordaine them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Surely it ſeemes vnto mee it was ordeined to thende this high Biſhop ſhould take on him the Aucthoritie to expounde the holie ſcriptures, and to the end hee ſhould enſtruct the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Chriſtian doctrine, not onely with woords but alſo with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of life, and to the ende he ſhould with teares and praiers make ſupplication continuallie vnto God, for his Chriſtian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to take on him the ſupreame charge and power to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue ſuch as had ſinned &amp; were deſirous to conuert themſelues, &amp; to pronounce damnation againſt ſuch as in their wicked liues remaine obſtinate. And to the ende that with continuall carefull endeuour hee ſhould procure the maintenance of the Chriſtian people in great peace and concord: and to the end wee ſhould haue here on earth ſuch a one as ſhould truelie and liuely repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto vs the life and holie cuſtome of Ieſus Chriſt our Rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, becauſe the hartes of men are much more allured with workes then with words. This is as much as I can gather out of the holie Scriptures, if you haue anie thing elſe, ſay it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>This ſhall ſuffice at this preſent, and ſee that you forget it not, for we ſhall haue need thereof hereafter in his due time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>No, I will not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then if I ſhew you plainlie, that becauſe the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour hath done that, which your ſelfe haue auerred to be his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: And becauſe the Pope hath refuſed to do that which on his part ought to haue bin done. This diſtruction of <hi>Rome</hi> hath fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed: In whom will you then lay the fault?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>If you could do this which I cannot beleeue, then is it plaine to be the Popes fault.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then I pray you tel me your ſelfe, ſeeing you ſay that the Pope was inſtituted to the ende hee ſhould imitate Ieſus Chriſt, what do you think that Ieſus Chriſt would rather main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his people in peace or to ſtir them vp and tormoile them in warres?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>This is cleere, that the Aucthor of Peace doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt any thing more then warre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then let vs ſee how ſhall he bee the Imitator of Chriſt Ieſu, that ſtirred vp warres and diſſolued peace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Such an one ſhould bee farre off from Imitation of Chriſt, but to what end aſke you mee this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:7"/>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>I demaund it for this purpoſe, that ſeeing the Emperor defending his Subiects, as he is bound: the Pope tooke armes againſt him, and diſſolued the peace, and raiſed a new warre in Chriſtendome, neither the Emperour was in fault for the euils that ſucceeded, ſeeing he did that which was his office and dutie: Neither can the Pope be excuſed of the fault, ſeeing hee did that he ought not haue doone, in breaking the peace and raiſing a new warre in Chriſtendome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>What peace did the Pope diſſolue, or what warre did he raiſe vp in Chriſtendome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>He diſſolued the peace that the Emperour had made with the French king, and hath ſtirred vp the warre which wee ſtill haue, whereby through the iuſt iudgement of God the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheefe came vpon him, which he hath receiued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Oh Sir, you make your account well, but where haue you learned that the pope ſtirred vp the warre with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and that hee diſſolued the peace made with the Frenche King.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe immediatly ſo ſoone as the French King was deliuered out of Priſon, he ſent him a writte, wherein he did ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue him of the othe which he had made vnto the Emperour, to the end he ſhould not be bound to accompliſh that which hee had promiſed, whereby more freelye hee might make warre vpon him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>But how knowe you this? you ſpeake as though you had bin of the Popes ſecret Councell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>It is knowne by manie meanes, but not to looſe time looke vpon the beginning of the league that the Pope made with the Frenche king, and you ſhall plainelie ſee, that the Pope was the aduancer of it, and ſeeing that this is ſo certaine a truth, that euen the Pope himſelfe confeſſeth it: dooth it ſeeme vnto you now that this was a deed fit for the Vicar of Ieſus Chriſt. You ſay that his office and dutie is to make peace among ſuch as are at difference, and he hath ſowne warres betweene thoſe that were in concord: you ſay his office was to teach the people both with words and workes, the doctrine of Chriſt Ieſu, and he hath taught all things cleane contrarie therevnto: you ſay his dutie was to pray vnto God for his people, and he hath gone about to worke their deſtruction: you ſay that his office was to imitate
<pb facs="tcp:1927:8"/> Ieſus Chriſt, and he in all things hath laboured to be contrarie vnto him: Ieſu Chriſt was poore and humble, but he to increaſe I wot not what Segnorie, hath put all Chriſtendome in armes. Ieſus Chriſt did good againſt ill, but he ill for good, in making a league againſt the Emperour, at whoſe handes he had receiued ſo much good. I ſaie not this to reprothe the Pope, it is well knowne it proceeded not of himſelfe, and that hee was irritated therevnto by ſome bad councell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>By this meanes ſhould he be wholie in the fault.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Both they that gaue him ſo bad councell, and himſelfe alſo that kept about him ſuch miſchieuous people, for doe you thinke that before God, a Prince ſhall be excuſed, by laying the fault in his Councell: No, no: for ſeeing God hath giuen him Iudgement to make choiſe of good men to be of his councell, and to aduiſe him to the beſt, if he chuſe ill men or retaine them about him, the fault is his, and if he haue no iudgement to chuſe ſuch perſons let him leaue his Segnorie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>You require things that are very harde and difficult.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And whie hard and difficult, dooth there need ſo great a iudgement for this matter. Tell me I pray you, what warre is there ſo iuſt, that a Vickar of Ieſus Chriſt ſhould take in hande againſt Chriſtians, the members of one body, whoſe head is Chriſt and his Vickar.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>The Pope had great reaſons to take in hand this warre againſt the Emperor, one for that he would not firſt ſeeke his freendſhip, and an other for that he held by vſurpation the ſtate of <hi>Millan,</hi> hauing deſpoiled the Duke <hi>Frauncis Sforza</hi> thereof, and the Pope ſeeing this feared another day he would do as much againſt him, taking from him alſo his territories of the Church: And therefore with great Iuſtice and reaſon did the Pope take Armes againſt the Emperour, aſwell to make him reſtore the Dutchie of <hi>Millane</hi> to the Duke, as alſo to aſſure the ſtate and territories of the Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>I woonder that a man of ſo good iudgement as you are, ſhould ſpeak a thing ſo far from reaſon as this, let vs ſee whether the Pope did this as the Vickar of Chriſt, or as <hi>Iulio de medicis.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>It is cleere that he did it as Vickar to Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then I ſaye if the Emperour would againſt all right and reaſon, deſpoile the Dukes of <hi>Millan</hi> of all his ſtate, what
<pb facs="tcp:1927:8"/> had the Pope to doe therewith, why would hee intermeddle in matters where he was not deſired, and in ſuch matters as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteined no wayes to his office: why did he not rather take ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample by Ieſus Chriſt to haue doone the contrarie? who being deſired, that in freendlie ſorte he would make Partition of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance betweene two kinſemen, he would not goe, leauing an example to his followers not to entermedle in ſo baſe matters, And would you now haue his Vickar to intrude himſelfe with an armed hand being not requeſted of them? where learne you that Ieſus Chriſt appointed his Vickar a Iudge betweene ſeculer Princes, how much leſſe an Executioner or brewer of war among Chriſtians? will you ſee how vnlike he is to be the Vicar of Chriſt that is a ſtirrer of wars, behold the fruites that proceed thereof, and ſee how contrarie they are, not onely to Chriſtian doctrine, but euen to humane nature? to all other creatures God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen weapons wherewith they might both defend themſelues and offend others: but man alone as a creature deſcended fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen, among whom there ſhould be all concord, as a thing that ſhould heere repreſent the image of God, he left him vnarmed, he meant not he ſhould make wars, he meant there ſhould be among men as great loue and concord, as there is among the Angels of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: &amp; yet notwithſtanding we are growne to ſo great blindneſſe, that more brute then the brute creatures, more beaſts then the beaſts themſelues, we do murther one another: the beaſts do liue in peace, but we much worſe then beaſts do liue in wars, if we wil make ſearche in all countries how men liue, in Chriſtendome on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie which is but a corner of the world, you ſhall find more warres then in all the world beſides. And yet are we not aſhamed to call our ſelues Chriſtians, &amp; for the moſt part ye ſhall finde them the moſt inflamers of wars, that ought moſt to appeaſe them: the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was bound ſeeing he would be the vicar of Chriſt Ieſu, The Cardinals were bound ſeeing they would be the pillers of the church: the biſhops were bound being paſtors, to giue their liues for their ſheepe, euen as Chriſt himſelf taught when he ſaid <hi>Bonus paſtor ponit Animam ſuam pro ouibus ſuis,</hi> but much more the Pope and Cardinals, ſeeing their reuenues were giuen to theſe Prelates to that ende, that vſing their paſtorall office they might the better protect and preſerue their people: but they for feare leaſt they ſhould looſe ſome little mite of their reputation
<pb facs="tcp:1927:9"/> put all Chriſtendom. O gentill Charitie, do I giue thee money to defend me, and dooſt thou therewith gather Souldiers together to murther me, to robbe me, and to deſtroie me? where learne you that Ieſus Chriſt commaunded his followers to make warres, Read all the Euangelicall doctrine. Read all the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Epiſtles, you ſhall finde nothing but peace, concord, vnitie, loue and charitie, when Ieſus Chriſt was borne, they entended no warres, but the very Angels ſoong <hi>Gloria in excelſis deo, in terra pax, hominibus bona voluntas,</hi> He gaue vs peace when he was borne, and peace when he was crucified, how oftentimes did he admoniſh and exhort his followers to this peace and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and yet not contented with this, he deſired of his father, that his ſhould be one among themſelues, euen as he and his Father were one, could he require a greater conformitie or vnitie? And yet furthermore, he required that thoſe which followed his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, ſhould not make themſelues different from others in gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, neither yet in their manner of behauiour, neither yet in faſting nor in any other externall matters, but onely in woorkes of charitie, this being the principall figure and meanes to knowe our faith, would you then haue the head thereof to walke ſo farre aſtraie? if ſeculer princes then make warres it is no maruell, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sheepe do but follow the Shepheard, if the head make warres the other members are forced to warre alſo. Of the Pope I cannot but maruell, that ſhould be a mirrour of al Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian vertues, and a patterne wherevpon we ſhould all caſt our eyes, being bound to maintaine all in peace and concorde (yea though it were with the perrill of his owne life) will notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding make warre to gaine and maintaine things which Ieſus Chriſt commaunded to be contemned, and that there ſhould bee found among Chriſtians any that would giue him ayde in an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo wicked, ſo execrable, &amp; preiudiciall to the honour of Chriſt, what blindneſſe is this? wee call our ſelues Chriſtians, and yet liue worſe then Turkes, yea worſe then brute beaſts: if we thinke that this doctrine of Chriſt be but a mockerie, whie doe wee not forſake it all together, for ſo at leaſt ſhould we not doe ſo great wrongs, where we haue receiued ſo great good. But ſeeing wee doe knowe it to be moſt true, and that we doe ſo much glorie in the name of Chriſtians, and diſdaine thoſe that be not: whie doe we not endeuoure to be Chriſtians indeed; whie doe we liue in
<pb facs="tcp:1927:9"/> ſort as if there were neither Faith nor Loue amongeſt vs?</p>
               <p>The Philoſophers and ancient Sages being gentils diſpiſed and contemned ritches, and would you haue the Vickar of Chriſt Ieſu make warres for that which thoſe blind Pagans eſteemed not. What ſhal thoſe Nations ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do know no more of Chriſt Ieſus then that which they behold in his Vickar, but that thoſe Philoſophers, who to attaine their true good which they had pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in vertue did deſpice theſe worldlie thinges, were much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then Ieſus Chriſt, when they ſee his Vickar bruing and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vp warres for theſe thinges which they contemned. Behold here the honor done vnto him by them that maintain themſelues vppon his bloud. Oh bloud of Ieſus Chriſt ſo euill be thy Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kars imploied, which by thee gather theſe maſſes of money to murder men, to murder Chriſtians, to diſtroy Cities, to ranſack villages, to diſhonour Virgins, to make ſuch numbers of Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes and Orphans, and to cauſe ſuch a multitude of miſchiefs, as warres drue with it: A man might ſee in <hi>Lumbardie,</hi> yea in all Chriſtendome, ſo great Proſperitie, ſo many and ſo goodlie citties, ſuch ſtatelie buildinges in the Suburbes and Countrie, ſuch Gardens, ſuch pleaſures, and ſo great paſtimes: The La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borers gathered their graines for their Flockes, and manured their landes. The Cittizens, Gentlemen, and Nobilitie, euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his degree emploied freelie their goods, they emploied qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly their inheritances, encreaſed their rents &amp; manie of them diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed largelie among the poore: But after this accurſed wars began, how manie citties haue wee ſeene deſtroied, how manie houſes and places of pleaſure diſpeopled and razed, how manie vineyards and Orchards ſpoiled and defaced, how many of the Nobilitie, Citizens, and Laborers falne into extream pouertie, how manie married women haue loſt their huſbandes, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Fathers and Mothers their deare children, how manie Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins their virginitie, how manie wiues forced in preſence of their Huſbandes, how many Huſbandes murdred in preſence of their Wiues, how many Nunns diſhonored, and what a ſlaughter and decay of men in Chriſtendome? and that worſe is, what a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Soules ſent to Hell? And doe wee winke at it as a matter of ieſt? And yet this Vicker of Chriſt not contented with all this, euen at this time when we were in peace commeth to ſtir vs vp a new warre, euen at this time I ſay when we haue the enemies
<pb facs="tcp:1927:10"/> of our Faith at our doore, to the ende wee may looſe the reſt as we loſt the kingdome of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> and to the end he might ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accompliſh the loſſe of all the reſidue that yet remained, Yea and yet further, his Souldiers not contenting themſelues to make warres like others ſeeke out new kindes of crueltie. For neither the Emperour <hi>Nero</hi> nor the <hi>Syracuſan Dyoniſius,</hi> nor all the cruel tirants that haue hetherto raigned in the world could inuent ſuch cruelties as this armie of the Popes after it brake the truce made with <hi>Don Hugo de Moncada</hi> hath put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution in the territorie of the <hi>Collones</hi> where two of theſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians haue taken a Virgin of the Nobilitie by the legs, and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her naked, her head downwards, an other comes with an balberd, all aliue as ſhee was cleeues her into two peeces: Oh crueltie, oh impietie, oh moſt execrable wickedneſſe, what could that poore wench haue committed, or what had thoſe wiues great with child offended, that in preſence of their huſbandes had their bellies ripped open with their cruell ſwords, and the infantes yet warm roſted on ſpits before the eies of the vnhappie mother. Oh woonderfull God that conſenteſt to theſe thinges. Oh eares of Men that can endure to heare ſuch a thing, oh ſupreame Biſhop that ſuffreſt theſe things to be done in thy name. What had thoſe innocent creatures merited? wee ſpeake ill of <hi>Herode</hi> that cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the children lately borne to be murdred, and thou conſenteſt to haue them murdered before they were borne: thou mighteſt haue ſuffered them at leaſt to haue receaued Baptiſme, thou ſhouldeſt not haue endeuored to haue deſtroied both ſoule and bodie. How had thoſe poore women merited to die with ſuch torment, to haue their bowels ripped open liuing, and to ſee their children groning vppon ſpits roſting, or thoſe ſorrowfull fathers that died with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie griefe of their vnfortunate Children and vnhappie Mothers? What Iewe, Turke, More, or Infidil wil now come to the Faith of Ieſus Chriſt, ſeeing wee receaue ſuch woorkes from his Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kars: which of them wil euer ſerue or honor him? And thoſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians which vnderſtand not the chriſtian doctrine, what haue they to do but to follow their Paſtor. And if euery one wil ſeeke to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, who wil deſire to liue among Chriſtians? ſhal we thinke ſir that this is to imitate Ieſus Chriſt? ſhall we thinke that this is to teach the Chriſtian people? ſhal we thinke that this is to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprete the ſacred Scriptures? ſhall we thinke that theſe bee the
<pb facs="tcp:1927:10"/> workes of Ieſus Chriſt? ſhal we thinke that to this ende this dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie was appointed, that by the ſame he ſhould deſtroy the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian people.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot denie it to bee an horrible thing, but this is a matter ſo accuſtomed in Italie to make no accompt of a Pope that maketh not war, as they hold it for a very great diſhonor for any Pope in his time to loſe any little percel of the landes of the Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Not to be tedious I wil omit a number of reaſons that I were able to alledge to confute this, but let vs come to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie: I ſay, that if the Emperour would goe about to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Church landes, what do you thinke? were it not better that the Pope had loſt all his temporall dignities, then that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome and the honor of Ieſu Chriſt ſhould ſuffer that it hath done?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>No ſurely, for thus would you goe about to ſpoile the Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And why ſpoile the Church, what call you the Church?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>The Pope and Cardinals.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And all the reſt of the Chriſtians ſhall they not as well bee the Church as they?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>They ſay yes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then the Seignorie and authoritie of the Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth rather in men then in gouernment of Townes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall the Church be wel eſtabliſhed when it ſhall haue many Chriſtians, and then diſpoiled when it ſhall haue few.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>That ſeemes to mee to be true.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Now then he that is the cauſe of the deſtruction of any one Chriſtian man, diſpoileth more the Church of Ieſus Chriſt then he that taketh from the Pope his temporall dignities.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Let it be ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then tel me now you, what number of Chriſtians haue periſhed ſince the Pope began this war, to aſſure as you ſay his eſtate? I omit the other miſchiefs which wars draweth on with it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Infinite.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lat.</speaker>
               <p>Now you ſee that hee that hath bin the cauſe of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction hath more deſpoiled the church then he that ſhould haue bereaued the Pope of his temporall dignitie: But let vs ſee if anie man ſhould haue caught from Ieſus Chriſt his Cloake,
<pb facs="tcp:1927:11"/> do you beleeue that he would haue taken Armes to haue defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>No ſurely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Why then would you haue the Pope to do it, ſeeing you ſay hee was appointed to that ende that he ſhould imitate Ieſus Chriſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>In this maner the Church ſhould neuer keep any Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norie, euerie one would pull a peece from it, if they thought the Pope might not defend it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Whether it bee neceſſarie or profitable to the Church, for the Popes to haue temporal ſeignories or not, let them look to that, but ſurely mee thinkes, they might much better intende matters ſpirituall, if they did not ſo much entangle themſelues with temporall, &amp; euen in that which you haue ſaid, you are much deceaued. For if the Pope would bee content to imitate Ieſus Chriſt, and liue indeede as his Vickar, hee ſhould not onely not loſe any part of his lands, but rather much more ſhould be giuen vnto him, and let vs ſee how he holds any thing of that hee hath but by that meanes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay the trueth, but now there is ſcarſely any chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>It is your ſelues with your euill liues that quench the fire of Charitie, and in your ſelues it lieth to kindle and enflame it, If you would.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>You would haue vs enflame charitie by looſing all wee haue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And why not? if it haue bene giuen you for Gods ſake, why ſhould you not bee content for Gods ſake to forgoe it. It is moſt certaine that all true Chriſtians ſhould ſo do, we hold &amp; poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe our goods temporal with this condicion, that we ſhould bee alwaies readie to leaue them whenſoeuer we ſhal ſee it conuent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for the honor and glorie of Chriſt Ieſus, and for the common good of Chriſtendome: how much more then ought you of the Clergie to do the ſame, yea, and how much more in dutie then ought the Vickar of Ieſus Chriſt to do it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>You are ſo holy as I neede not meddle with you, ſuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we haue no neede of ſuch at <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Nether would I deſire to liue among ſuch wicked people?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>You meane as there are now there:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:11"/>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Neither yet as theſe that were there, for in an infected flocke there is bad choiſe to be made.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>What? do you then account vs as bad as thoſe Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>As bad? Ney I would you were not much worſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Wherefore.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe you are much more pernitious vnto the whole commonweale by your bad example.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>And I pray you what be they?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>They make not profeſſion to be the miniſters of God as you doe, neither haue they liuing for ſuch as they haue, neither is there any that will ſeeke or ought to ſeeke to immitate them, as they ſhould you. But ſtaie a while, I haue not yet doone, for he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto haue I handled this matter, calling the Pope Chriſts vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car: now will I handle it, making accoumpt or ſuppoſing the Pope is alſo a ſecular Prince as the Emperour, to the end you may the more cleerely ſee the Error you were in. And as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the firſt, it is moſt certaine that the Pope receiued this dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie by the fauour of the Emperour, and hauing ſo gotten it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold what gratitude, immediatlie he comforts himſelfe with the King of Fraunce at his entrance into Italie, and left the freend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Emperour. Yea and ſome auerre that the Pope him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was the ſoliſitor and cauſer of his entrance into Italie, and notwithſtanding all this, the Emperour hauing the victorie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the French King, was not onely content not to take from the Pope his territories of <hi>Parma</hi> and <hi>Placentia,</hi> as both in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Reaſon he mought then haue doone, but ratified the league that his Embaſſadour made with him, yet the Pope not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding not contented with this, began to frame a newe league in Italie againſt the Emperour after the Frenche King was Priſoner. But that ſecret practiſe was diſcouered, and ſo tooke no effect. And yet could not all this ſo alienate the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours minde, but that hee ſought by all honeſt and reaſonable meanes to content the Pope, and to procure him to be a meane in that peace, which was intreatie betweene him and the King of Fraunce, and that he ſhould not hinder it, but he was neuer able to attaine it. Yet in the meane time was this peace concluded with Fraunce, but ſo ſoone as the King was ſet at libertie, the Pope began to procure a new league with him againſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour,
<pb facs="tcp:1927:12"/> hauing receiued no occaſion in the world at his hands ſo to doe, and all this euen at that time, when the Turkes with a puiſant Armie began to enter by the kingdome of <hi>Hungary,</hi> doe you thinke that this was a good parte? The enemies were come to our gates, and we brew warres within the houſe. He requires the Emperour that he ſhould not prepare any forces to reſiſt the Turke, and yet himſelfe ſecretly prepareth to make warre vpon the Emperor. Do you thinke that theſe were works of a Chriſtian Prince?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>But let vs ſee on the other ſide why the Emperour did not iuſtice to the Duke of <hi>Millan,</hi> for if he had comitted no fault, was it not good reaſon he ſhould reſtore his ſtate to him againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Yes ſurely, and therefore ſir, behold the Emperor pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>Frauncis Sforſa</hi> in the ſtate of <hi>Millan,</hi> whereas he might haue tane it to himſelfe, ſeeing he hath much more right there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto then that Duke, and that onely for the peace and eaſe of Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and all Chriſtendome, he was content to beſtowe it on ſuch a man, at whoſe hands he neuer had receiued any ſeruice. And afterward the Emperour vnderſtood by his Captaines that the ſame Duke had conference, and had taken parte in that league which the Potentates of Italie had made againſt him. And ſeeing therein he had committed treaſon, it was good reaſon, that as a rebell diſgraded, he ſhould be depriued of his ſtate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>And how will you depriue a man vnheard?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And why not? when the fault is euident and manifeſt, or by delay might enſue inconuenience, as at that time when the armie of the Emperour was in extreame danger, if it had not poſſeſſed it ſelfe of the Citties and Villages in the ſtate of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>But whie did not the Emperour afterwards cauſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirie to be duely made, to haue vnderſtood the truthe, and then to haue reſtored the ſtate vnto him, if hee had beene found fault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And where haue you ſeene a man accuſed in cauſes cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall to anſwer by a Procter, eſpecially in matter of treaſon: he might haue preſented himſelfe and ſo haue beene tryed by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Iuſtice. But that abſenting of himſelfe did ſufficiently prooue he was culpable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>He feared the Captaines of the Emperour, whome
<pb facs="tcp:1927:12"/> he knew to beare him ſmall good will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>In good faith he feared his owne iniuſtice, for behould ſo ſoone as he was eſcaped out of the Caſtell of <hi>Millaine,</hi> he ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned himſelfe with the enemies of the Emperour. But what had the Pope to doe in that matter, if a Prince will puniſh his Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, hath he to intermeddle therein? Or if he had to doe therewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and that it did appertaine vnto his office, was it not ſufficient that the Emperour had referred all to <hi>Don Hugo di Moncada,</hi> offering him all that he could demaund. What man is there in the world that would not rather enioy one with peace, then two with warres? if the Pope ſo much deſired that the Duke <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Sforſa</hi> ſhould be reſtored to his eſtate, onely, becauſe neither the Emperour ſhould enioye it himſelfe, nor ſhould giue it to the infant <hi>Don Hernando</hi> his kinſman, why did he not accept that which <hi>Don Hugo di Moncada</hi> did offer on the parte of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, who was content that the ſaid ſtate ſhould reſt in the power of the <hi>Treceros,</hi> till ſuch time as the right of the Duke might be ſeene, and that if he were not in fault in thoſe matters he was charged, that then he ſhould be immediatly reſtored, and if he were found in fault, and that he ought to be depriued, yet the Emperour promiſed, that neither he would take it to himſelfe, nor beſtowe it on the Infant <hi>Don Hernando,</hi> but on the Duke of <hi>Burboune,</hi> who was one of thoſe that by the Pope himſelfe was firſt ſet downe for it. But will you that I tell you? the Pope ment to hold it himſelfe, and thought that the Armie of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour being defeated, they ſhould be able not onely to turne him out of <hi>Lumbardie,</hi> but alſo out of Italie, and to take from him his kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> as they had agreed and made parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion among themſelues. And vpon this hope the Pope would not accept of that which by <hi>Don Hugo</hi> the Emperour had offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>It was not for any ſuch matter, but only becauſe he was in league with others, he would not breake his faith with them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>This is a gentle excuſe, but I pray you why ſhould he rather obſerue his faith giuen to the French King, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Chriſtendome, then his former othe giuen to the Emperour for remedie of the ſame, he ſhould much rather haue broken the latter giuen to the French King, then the firſt giuen to the Emperour. Doe you not knowe, that a vowe made
<pb facs="tcp:1927:13"/> to the hurte or preiudice of your neighbour, ought not to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, how much more then ſuch an oth as tendeth to the hurte of all Chriſtendome, the diſhonour of GOD, and deſtruction of ſuch a multitude of people as haue ſuffered by meanes thereof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Surelie in this I muſt confeſſe you haue very great reaſon, but you conſider not how the Emperours armie mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to inuade the Territories of the Pope, and that the Pope as a good Prince ſeeing you will ſo call him, is bound to defend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and you knowe well euen the lawe of nature permitteth euerye man to defend his owne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>If the Pope would haue kept the league which he had made with the Emperour, or would haue accepted that which was newly offered vnto him, his armie would neuer haue threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to haue entred on the Popes territorie. And yet if all were as your ſelfe ſaie, and that the lawe of Nature permitteth euery man to defend his owne: yet tell me, do you Iudge that Princes haue the ſame Authority ouer their people, that you haue ouer your Mule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Wherefore not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe Beaſtes are made for the ſeruice of Man, but Man onely for the ſeruice of God, let vs ſee, were Princes made for the people, or people for the Princes ſake?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Surely I beleeue Princes were ordeined for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſake.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then a good Prince without reſpect of his perticular intereſt, is bound to procure the good of his people onely, ſeeing for their ſake he was ordeined.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed in reaſon it ought ſo to be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Well then let vs put the caſe, that the Emperors Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie woulde haue inuaded and poſſeſſed the Territories of the Church, and let vs conſider whether were better for the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, that the Pope ſhould freely haue ſurrendred to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, or in defence of them to doe as he hath doone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Surely if we ſhall haue regard onely to the profit of the people, there is no doubt if the Pope had freely giuen all thoſe territories to the Emperour, they ſhould not haue ſuffered ſo great damage as they haue doone, but ſhewe me a Prince that will doe this.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>I will ſhew you euen the Emperour himſelfe, doe you
<pb facs="tcp:1927:13"/> not know that he might with verie great reaſon and iuſtice haue tane to himſelfe both the Dukedome of <hi>Millane</hi> and the Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norie of <hi>Genua,</hi> ſeeing there is not any that haue ſo good right to them as himſelfe. But becauſe he ſaw it was better for the good of the people that hee ſhould beſtow the one on <hi>Frauncis Sforza,</hi> and in the other to eſtabliſh the <hi>Adorni,</hi> he did it franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and liberallie, leſſe regarding his owne benefite then the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique weale, as euery good Prince ought.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>If al men ſhould do that they ought to do, then both ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and temporall, all ſhould be the Popes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>The Popes, and why?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe he would gouerne them better and more holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then any other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And are you not aſhamed to ſay ſo? do you not know, that there are not any territories worſe gouerned then thoſe of the Church?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes I know it wel, but I thought you had not known it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>But let vs conſider alſo if the Pope plaied the part of a good Prince in taking Armes againſt the Emperour, at whoſe handes hee had receiued ſo many benefites, breaking the peace &amp; friendſhip he held with him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>The Pope did not take Armes againſt the Emperour, but againſt that vnbrideled armie that committed horrible extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and other abhominable things in the ſtate of <hi>Millane,</hi> and right and reaſon would, thoſe poore people ſhould be deliuered from that Tirannie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>I meruaile that you ſhould ſay ſuch a thing, for let vs ſee if the Pope would haue mainteined frendſhip with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, what ſhould his Maieſtie haue needed to haue kept an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie in Italie ſeeing he had ſo lately giuen commaundement to diſcharge it, but when he vnderſtood of the league made againſt him, he was then conſtrained to continue it, if the Pope preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded nothing but the libertie &amp; reſtitution of the Duke of <hi>Millane</hi> and to free that ſtate of the vexations of the Emperours Army, and to aſſure the Church landes. Why did hee not embrace the Emperours friendſhip, by the which all might haue bin remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſeeing the ſame was alſo deſired at his hands: if the Pope had deſired no more then you ſpeake of, what fault had the kingdome of <hi>Naples</hi> committed that they ſhould deuide, it among them?
<pb facs="tcp:1927:14"/> what had the cities of <hi>Genua</hi> and <hi>Sena</hi> committed, that the one by ſea and the other by land ſhould be beſieged? he would pretend to remedy the extorſions and ſpoils of the armie in <hi>Lumbardie,</hi> and yet indeed not onely encreaſed them there, but gaue occaſion to make them far greatter through all Italie: yea euen through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Chriſtendome. Read the league made between the Pope, the K. of France, the Venetians &amp; the Florentines, and there ſhal you ſee euen that which the Pope ſought, what had the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour done vnto him, why hee ſhould take Armes againſt him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Did I not tell you that the Pope did not take Armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Emperor, but onely againſt his vnbrideled Armie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>So that this war then was onely againſt the Armie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>No otherwiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lat.</speaker>
               <p>Why then if the war were vpon the Armie, &amp; the Armie haue reuenged it ſelf, wherfore lay you the fault in the Emperor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe the Emperor did ſuſtein them, &amp; ſent them new ſupplie, wherwith they might be able to do that they haue done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Did not your ſelfe ſay that the Emperors office &amp; dutie was to defend his Subiects and to do iuſtice: If the Pope then would miſuſe them, and ſeeke to poſſeſſe his kingdoms and ſeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nories, and to hinder him from doing Iuſtice vppon the Duke of <hi>Millan,</hi> as he was bound, of force hee was conſtrained to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein &amp; encreaſe his army to be able to defend and relieue them, or els in leauing to do ſo, he ſhould haue left to be a good Emperor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>In this you haue reaſon, but I pray you tell mee, do you thinke it was wel done of the Emperor to ſend <hi>Don Hugo,</hi> and the <hi>Colloneſes</hi> to make that attempt on <hi>Rome?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>The Emperor neuer did it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>What? did not the Emperour giue commaundement that <hi>Don Hugo</hi> and the <hi>Colloneſi</hi> together ſhould iointly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Rome,</hi> and apprehend the Pope?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>No, he did it not, but if hee had done it, do you thinke it had bin ill done?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Oh my God, And would you take vppon you to defend that too?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Yea ſurely, and tel me I pray you if your ſelfe had a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that had ſo far loſt his wits and ſenſes, that with his owne hands would goe about to kill and teare his owne children, what would you do?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:14"/>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Hauing no other remedie I would either ſhut him vp, or bind his hands till he returned to his wits againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And ſhould you not thinke that for your brothers ſake al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it were your dutie and charge ſo to do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes ſurely it is plaine I ought to take care and charge al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then tell mee, the Pope is hee not a ſpiritual Father of all Chriſtians?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yea.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>La.</speaker>
               <p>Then if he with wars go about to deſtroy his owne Children do you not thinke it ſhal be a good &amp; merciful deed aſwel towards him, as alſo towardes his Children to endeuor to take away from him the power to do this harme, you cannot denie me this.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arc.</speaker>
               <p>Wel, but al this while ſee you not how great damage &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honor done to Ieſus Chriſt to handle in this maner his Vickar?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, rather there is done vnto him great ſeruice, by auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this ill that his Vickar through the bad councel that he kepes about him, ſhould not be the cauſe of the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of people, for whom Ieſus Chriſt died aſwel as for him, and belieue me euen the Pope himſelfe, when laying aſide his paſſions he ſhal com to a right knowledge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth, will be excedingly wel pleaſed with it, that hath taken away from him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> meanes wherby he might otherwiſe haue done ſo great an harme: if not I pray you tell me, if your ſelfe (which God forbid) ſhould be ſo far out of your wits, as that with your own teeth you ſhould bite and teare your owne fleſh, and members of your own body, would you not be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular wel pleaſed with him, &amp; hold your ſelf much bound vnto him that ſhould hold and ſtay you till you came to your wits againe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>This is cleere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lat.</speaker>
               <p>Then behold how all wee Chriſtians are members of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and haue for our head the ſame Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay truth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then if this his Vickar by the bad councell he hath about him be the occaſion of the perdition and murder of his own proper members which are the Chriſtians, ſhall he not bee ſingularly well pleaſed with him, that ſhall hinder and let him from doing ſo great an euill?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Without doubt you ſay the truth, but euery man cannot attaine this vnderſtanding nor can iudge a right farther then they can ſee, and therefore Princes ſhould be very wary what they do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:15"/>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Much more are the Princes bound vnto God then vnto men, &amp; more regard ſhould they haue of the iudgement of wiſe men then of fools. It were a goodly matter that a Prince ſhould leaue to do the dutie which he oweth for the ſeruice of God, and welfare of his countrie, for feare of that which the blinde multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude ſhould iudge or ſpeake. Let a Prince do that he ought, and let the multitude prate what they liſt: for ſo they iudged of <hi>Dauid</hi> becauſe he daunced before the Arke of the Teſtament. So they iudged of Ieſus Chriſt, becauſe he died vppon the Croſſe, when they ſaid he ſaued others, but could not ſaue himſelf, euen ſo they iudged of the Apoſtles, becauſe they preached Chriſt Ieſus: euen ſo they iudge in theſe daies of thoſe which endeuor to become true Chriſtians indeed, diſpiſing the vanity of this world, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the right path of the truth. And who is there that can eſcape the falſe iudgements of the common people? Rather wee ſhould thinke that verie good which of the multitude is condemned for bad, and contrariwiſe. But wil you know the truth? Mallice and craft they call induſtrie, Auarice and Ambicion they cal Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimitie, the ſlaunderous Backbiter a good Companion: a vaine diſſembling Liar they term a gallant Courtier: the ſubtle decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they call a wiſe man: and contrariwiſe a good and vertuous man is called ſimple. If any man in chriſtian humility make ſmal accompt of this Worldes vanitie, they ſay he is become a foole. Such a one as for Gods ſake diſtributes his goods to the poore, they ſay is prodigal. And ſuch a one as by practiſes and deceipts wil not ſeek for honor and welth they ſay he is a man of no valure. and ſuch a one as for the loue of Chriſt forgeueth iniuries, they call a coward and a man of ſmal courage. Finally conuerting ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues into vices, and vices into vertues, the lewd and wicked they terme happy and fortunate, and the good and vertuous poor and vnhappie. And notwithſtanding all this they are not aſhamed to vſurpe the names of chriſtians hauing no ſigne or marke thereof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Surely I am of this minde, that although you ſay the trueth, yet your ſelf being young, a ſeculer perſon, &amp; a Courtier, you ſhould do better to leaue theſe matters to deuines: but this I ſay, let all be as you haue declared, yet let vs ſee at leaſt whether it had not bin reaſon whoſoeuer began this trouble, that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour ſhould haue chaſtiſed thoſe which ſacked the holy Pallace and the church of <hi>S. Peeter.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:15"/>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Sir it had bin much better that the Pope ſhould not haue broken the league nor his faith that he gaue to <hi>Don Hugo.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>It was not he that broke it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Who then made warres vpon the <hi>Colloneſi.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>He made thoſe warres not in the name of the Pope, but in the name of the Colledge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Neuer tell me theſe childiſh fables, whoſe were the Captaines? whoſe were the Souldiers? who paid them? whoſe were the Enſignes? to whome ought they obedience? Theſe are toyes to mocke Children. But I woonder who they were that inuented ſuch a vanitie, and alſo of the Cardinals that gaue their conſent to haue it doone in their name. But it is very well, ſeeing God hath well chaſtized them for it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Would you not haue the Pope chaſtize the <hi>Colloneſi</hi> being his owne ſubiects.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Noe, ſeeing he had giuen his faith not to doe it, and brake his league ſo oft as hee tooke armes againſt them, and hee knew the Emperour ought not to giue his conſent, ſeeing the <hi>Colloneſi</hi> were aſwell his ſubiects as the Popes, and he bound as a good Prince to defend his ſubiects.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>But let vs then ſee foraſmuch as after this league was broken, there was on the one ſide and the other ſo much hurte doone, wherefore did not the Emperor obſerue the other league which the Viceroy of <hi>Naples</hi> made with the Pope, at that time when a great part of that kingdome was loſt, and all the reſt in manifeſt perrill to be gone?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>What would not the Emperour obſerue it? Nay I tell you truely, that when the Capitulations of that truce came to his hands, albeit the conditions therof were vniuſt, and againſt the honour and reputation of the Emperour, yet did his Maieſtie preſently without regard of that which the Pope had ſo diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtlie doone) in giuing the Inueſtidure of his kingdomes vnto ſuch as had no manner right vnto them (a matter for the verye Children to laugh at) he did ratifie and approoue the league ſhewing how much he deſired the friendſhip of the Pope, and to ſtand in good tearmes with him, ſeeing he choſe rather to accept ſuch vniuſt conditions, then to proſequute the iuſt reuenge which he had in his hands. But by the permiſſion of God, who had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to chaſtice theſe iniuries, the capitulations ſtaid ſo long
<pb facs="tcp:1927:16"/> in ſending hether, and the ratification in going thether, that before all was finiſhed, that was done which we heereof paſſed in <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſurely if you will iudge rightly, there was none in fault but the very Pope himſelfe, who when he might haue liued in peace, ſought for warre, and that truce hee rather made for neceſſitie then mooued by vertue, when he ſawe with what determination the Emperours Armie went to <hi>Rome.</hi> But was it not more reaſon that you ſhould haue obſerued the league yee made with <hi>Don Hugo,</hi> for hauing ſo broken the former, what could there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoped but that ye would do the like now, if the Army ſhould haue returned. But ſeeing the army would not returne, why did you not moderate thoſe conditions that yee had put into that truce, and ſo both the Armie had returned, and <hi>Rome</hi> remained free.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Would you that the Pope ſhould haue giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> money.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And why not? if he had it to giue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>What if he had to giue being no way bound to doe it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>How was he not bound? wherefore then doe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans giue vnto him the rents and reuenues he hath.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe he ſhould beſtow &amp; ſpend them in thoſe things that ſhould be moſt profitable for the Chriſtian commonweale.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And what could haue bin more profitable then to haue cauſed that armie to haue turned backe againe? This is cleere that although matters in the end ſhould haue falne out euen as the Pope deſired, yet that Armie going forward there could not haue been eſcaped many murthers beſides ſuch other miſchiefes as warres draweth on with it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay the truth, but why did not the Emperour pay his Armie, that it might haue bin obedient to his Captaines, for it is well knowne, it was not the fault of the Duke of <hi>Burbone,</hi> that the truce was not obſerued, but the Armie would not obey him, becauſe it was not paid, and this was the Emperors fault.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>The Emperour paide not his Souldiers that he had there, becauſe he had not wherewithall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Then ſeeing he had not wherewithall to pay his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, why would he make warre?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>But why do you the ſame your ſelues, and therby enforce him to keep an army to defend himſelf, for the emperor ful gladly would haue liued in peace, if your ſelues had not made the war.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Nay ſomwhat more I can tell you, that if his armie had
<pb facs="tcp:1927:16"/> not made ſuch extreame diligence, it ſhould haue had enough to doe to haue defended him, for I doe verely beleeue before this daye hee ſhould not haue had left him a foote of grounde in <hi>Italie.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>How ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>The Pope was then in making another league, much more terrible then the firſt, wherevnto the King of England alſo ſhould haue entred, and the Pope promiſed to excommunicate the Emperour, and all thoſe on his part, and to depriue him of his kingdomes of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Scicilia,</hi> and to continue a new warre vpon him till ſuch time as they had enforced him to reſtore vnto the French king his Sonnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>A gentle peece of worke I promiſe you, but had it not beene better to haue brought to paſſe that the armie might haue returned then to kindle a new fire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Better no doubt: but to conclude, men are men, and cannot at all times commaund themſelues according to the rule of reaſon. But I pray you come neerer, albeit in all that you haue ſayd, you haue the greateſt reaſon in the world, yet in good faith doe you thinke it well doone, that with thoſe <hi>Almans</hi> worſe then heretikes, and that with that ſcomme of <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Italians</hi> that haue neither faith nor lawe. The Emperour ſhould ſuffer that ſacred Cittie of <hi>Rome</hi> to be deſtroied, the which (bee it good or bee it bad) in concluſion it is the head of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, he ought to haue had an other manner of regarde there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>I haue already plainely ſhewed you, that this was not doone neither by the commaundement nor by the will of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and further that your ſelues began to make the warre, when there was a truce, and notwithſtanding the Emperour ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified the peace ſo ſoone as it was preſented.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>But why ſhould he keepe in <hi>Italie</hi> ſuch wicked people as like rauenous Woolues ſhould come to deſtroie that holye Cittie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>If you your ſelues would haue bin contented to haue liued in peace, &amp; not haue made war vpon the Emperor when he did nothing againſt you, there had beene indeed no cauſe why he ſhould haue mainteined or ſent any ſuch people into <hi>Italie</hi> would you haue it lawfull for your ſelues to make warres vpon vs, and
<pb facs="tcp:1927:17"/> not lawfull for vs to defend our ſelues. This were in deed a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle manner of liuing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Well let it be lawfull for you in Gods name, but yet not with Infidels and Heretikes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Surely you ſpeake very badlie heerein, for as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Almanes,</hi> you cannot be certaine that they are <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans,</hi> neither is it likely or credible conſidering they were ſent by King <hi>Ferdinando</hi> his brother, that dooth perſequute the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans.</hi> But you your ſelfe haue receiued into your Armie <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans</hi> that were fled out of <hi>Almany,</hi> and with them haue you made warres vpon the Emperour. And as concerning the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> and <hi>Italians,</hi> which you call Infidels, if your meaning be to call wicked liuing Infidilitie. Who are then more Infidels then your ſelues, for where may a man finde more vices, yea or ſo many or ſo publique, or ſo free of puniſhment as in your court of <hi>Rome?</hi> or who euer committed ſo great and abhominable cruelties as that Armie of the Pope in the territories of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loneſi?</hi> if thoſe of the Emperors bee Infidels for liuing ſo ill, why are not thoſe of yours Infidels that are much worſe? If it be lawfull for you to make warres with people that you your ſelues repute Infidels, why ſhall it not be lawful for vs to defend our ſelues with a people that we take not to be Infidels? what a mockerie is this. That which you doe againſt the Emperour, you do it not againſt him but againſt his Armie, but that the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie dooth againſt you, is not doone by the Armie but by the Emperour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Well let vs ſay the Army did it without commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without conſent, and againſt the will of the Emperour, And that his Maieſtie was in no faulte, let vs then ſee when it was doone, whye hath hee not puniſhed the offendours and ill dooers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe he knoweth it to be a thing rather diuine then humane. And becauſe he is accuſtomed rather to do good for ill, then ill for good. And a gentill toye it were for him to chaſtice and puniſhe thoſe that venter their liues for him, and in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Well then ſeeing ye will not chaſtice and puniſh them, yet why would ye be any longer ſerued with ſuch a people as had committed ſo horrible and abhominable outrage,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:17"/>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>For two reſpects, firſt to auoid the miſchiefe they would haue done being diſbanded or caſhed, and alſo to reſiſt the flames that your ſelues had kindled: For a mockerie had it beene at that time when the French were marching into Italie for the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to caſh or diſſolue his Armie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot well tell what to replie, and ſurely in this you haue verie fullie perfourmed your promiſe, and in this I muſt confeſſe I was much abuſed. But now I would deſire you to open vnto mee the cauſes why God hath permitted the euilles which haue bin done in <hi>Rome,</hi> ſeeing you ſay it hath bene for the great good of Chriſtendome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Seeing in the firſt you reſt ſatiſfyed I doubt not by Gods helpe but to leaue you much better contented in the ſecond, but ſeeing it now late, wee will leaue that part for after dinner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I meane now to deteine you for my gueſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>It ſhal bee ſir as you commaund, for hether we may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes returne againe.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <head>The ſecond part.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lattantio.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O accompliſh now that, which I haue promiſed you, hauing alreadie halfe done in performing the firſt part, ye wil not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie me that all the vices &amp; al the deceipts that the mallice of Man was able to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, was not conioined togither in that Cittie, which with great reaſon ye name the holie Citie, becauſe it ought ſo to be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Surely therin you haue great reaſon, and God knoweth what I alwaies thought of that matter, and what I felt at hart to ſee that Citie which in reaſon ought to be euen the patterne of vertues to all the world, to be ſo full of vices, chafferie, deceipt, and manifeſt villeinies: Such ſale made of Offices, Benefices, Buls, Indulgences, and Diſpenſations, ſo ſhameleſlie, that in verie trueth it ſeemed a verie mockerie of the Chriſtian Faith, and that the Miniſters of the Church tooke no other care but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:1927:18"/> to inuent means to ſcrape money. The Pope pawned certaine Apoſtles, that he had of Gold, and afterwards made an impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be leuied by Buls, <hi>pro redemptione Apoſtolorum.</hi> It is ſtraunge they were not aſhamed to commit thinges ſo foule and preiudiciall to their owne dignitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>The very ſame ſay all they that come thence, and the ſame did I my ſelfe know when I was there: But come you he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: If your Sonnes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Ah ſir ſpeake courteouſlie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Pardon mee, I remembred not you were a Clarke, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit yee haue manie Clarkes that take no ſhame to haue Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but this ſpeech I onely vſe for an example.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Well then, ſpeake on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>If your Sonnes ſhould happen to haue a verie vicious and bad Scholemaiſter, and that you did perceaue that by his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and bad manners hee did infect them, what would you do?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>I would manie times admoniſh him that he ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, but if he would not do it, I would vſe my aucthoritie ouer him, and chaſtice him gently, that for feare of ill he ſhould amend, if he would not for the loue of good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then behold heere God is Father to vs all, and hath deliuered vs vnto the Pope as vnto our Scholemaiſter, to the end wee ſhould learne of him, and of thoſe that are about him to liue like Chriſtians. But ſeeing the vices of that court of <hi>Rome,</hi> were ſuch and ſo great, that they infected theſe Children of God, &amp; that wee did not onely not learn of them the doctrine of Chriſt, but rather a manner of life moſt contrarie, God ſeeing that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Prophets, the Euangeliſtes, nor ſuch a number of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Doctors as haue written in times paſt, reprouing vices, and praiſing vertues, could moue them that liued wickedly to amend and liue like Chriſtians, he ſought out new means to draw them to do their duties. And beſides manie other verie good Maiſters and Preachers ſent vs in times paſt, hee hath ſent euen in theſe our daies that excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Man <hi>Eraſmus Roterodamus,</hi> who with much eloquence, prudence, and modeſtie, in manie of his workes, diſcouering the vices and deceipts of the Romans Court, and in generall of all the Perſons Eccleſiaſticall, a man would haue thought it had bin ynough to haue mooued all ſuch as in that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling liued ſo wickedly to haue amended for very ſhame of thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:1927:18"/> thinges were ſpoken of them. But when this would nothing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite them, but that their wickedneſſe rather daily more and more encreaſed, God ſought a new meane to conuert them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore permitted that Frier <hi>Martin Luther</hi> to riſe vp, who ſhould not onely vtterlie ſhame them, declaring without any reſpect all their vices, but ſhould alſo draw a number of people from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of theſe prelats, to the end y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch as would not be moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with ſhame might at leaſt for coueteouſnes of their worldly wealth be reformed, ſeeing how much yee ſhould looſe by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolt of Almanie, or for ambition, ſeeing how great a Seignorie yee ſhould part withal if Almanie ſhould fall from your obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in ſort as preſently it doth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>But that Friar hath not onely ſpoken euil of vs but alſo of God in a thouſand hereſies that he hath written.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay the truth, but if your ſelues had not firſt amended that which with great reaſon he reprooued and not irritated him farther with your excommunications, perhaps hee neuer would haue broken out into thoſe hereſies, which afterwards he wrote, nether ſhould yee haue had in Germanie ſo great a diſtruction of ſoules and bodies, as ſince by meanes therof hath happened.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>But ſtay ſir, this could not be remedied without a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel general, &amp; they ſay it was not fit at that time to cal a councell, for that it had bin a manifeſt betraying of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eccleſiaſtical perſons, ſo as if at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time we ſhould haue called a general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel, we might haue gone al to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hoſpital, &amp; the Pope too with vs for company.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>How ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>The whole ſtates of the Empire preſented certaine wrongs, which they ſaid they receaued of the apoſtolik Sea &amp; of many perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s eccleſiaſtical, &amp; in euery point they required redres,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And why then did you not redreſſe them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Therabout we went, but they alledged that ſeeing the rents of the church were giuen and appointed for reliefe and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour of the poore that they ſhould bee ſpent that way, and not in warres, nor in vices, nor in pride as at this day for the moſt part they are. And then they farther deſired that the people and not the clergie ſhould haue the adminiſtration of them. And then they deſired that no diſpenſation ſhould be giuen for money, alledging that aſwell the poore were the Children of God as the ritch, and that giuing diſpenſations for money, the Poore who in reaſon
<pb facs="tcp:1927:19"/> ſhould be moſt priueledged were moſt oppreſſed, and the Ritch contrariwiſe moſt priueledged.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And were not you in that as I haue often bene and ſtill am aſtoniſhed in ſuch ſort as I know not what to ſay, I ſee on the one ſide that Chriſt praiſeth pouerty and inuiteth vs with his moſt perfect example thereunto, but on the other ſide, I ſee wee can ſcarſly get any thing of his Miniſters but for money, at Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme money, at Biſhoping money, at Mariage money, at Holy Orders money, for Confeſſion money, for diſcharge of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications money, no not Extreame Vnction without money, they will ring no Bels without money, no Buriall in the Church without money, no hearing of Maſſe in times of Interdiction without money: So that it ſeemeth by them, that Paradize is ſhut vp from them that haue no money. Then what meaneth this that the Ritche is buried in the Church and the poore in the Church yard. If Chriſt had meant that his Church ſhould haue bin more partiall to the Ritch, then to the Poore, why doth hee councell vs to pouertie? The Ritch man may marrie with his neereſt kin, but the poore not ſo, albeit he be readie to die for loue of her. The Ritch may eate fleſh in Lent, but the poore may not, albeit Fiſh perhaps be much dearer. The ritch man readily get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth large indulgences, but the poore none, becauſe hee wanteth money to pay for them. And of this manner yee ſhall finde an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of other thinges: and you ſhall not want of them, that will alledge manie things to be done for the ſeruice of God as to found Churches and Monaſteries, to ſay many Maſſes, &amp; manie Trentals, and to buye many Tapers to burne vpon your Sepulture. Ieſus Chriſt doth councell mee to diſpiſe and leaue all theſe worldly thinges to follow him, and thou doſt councel me to ſeeke them. You ſhould do me a verie great pleaſure to ſhew me the reaſon they can alledge for it, for as God ſhall ſaue mee, I neither know, nor can conceaue anie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>In good faith yee are now climing a good Tree, but heare you? I neuer brake my Braine about theſe matters that could yeeld mee no profite.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Now wel mought you thee I pray God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Beſides all this they ſaid, that when vnto the Clergie theſe liberties and Immunities were firſt giuen, which yet they hold, they were then poore &amp; imparted that they had with others
<pb facs="tcp:1927:19"/> that were in want more then themſelues, but now they are much more ritch then their founders, and that it ſeemed neither honeſt nor reaſonable, that the poorer ſort of the people ſhould be burde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with impoſitions, when the Cleargie vpon whom they ſpent all ſhould be exempted. They ſaid alſo that they had ſo many feaſts dayes to obſerue, that workemen and labourers receiued great preiudice thereby, and that by proofe it was ſeene, that men vpon thoſe daies did not exerciſe themſelues in ſuch matters as they ought, but in other matters much worſe, then vpon other daies, ſo that it were conuenient alſo to haue ſome moderation of theſe holy dayes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And what do you thinke that they ſpake amiſſe therein.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>And will you defend them to? Doe you not ſee that thoſe Saints whoſe feaſts you would aboliſh would be offended, and thereby ſome great ill might happen vnto vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Yea but doe not you ſee that thoſe Saints haue much more cauſe to be offended with the vices and villanies committed vpon thoſe feſtiuall dayes, then if men did onely worke for their liuing. Surely if men did truely ſerue God vpon theſe feſtiuall dayes, I would wiſh euery day feſtiuall, but ſeeing this is not doone, I cannot hold it ill, that they were moderated, if a man play the drunkard, or play all day at Boules or at Dice, or wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der about women or other like villanies, we thinke we haue not broken the feaſt. But if another forced by extreame neceſſitie worke to get his meate, preſently they ſay this is an heretike. I cannot ſkill of theſe ſeruices, it greeueth men to ſee ritch men vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe dayes to take all their pleaſures, and to laye the whole burthen on the vnhappy Artificers, labourers, and poore men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>For all this that you haue ſaid we make no great rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning, we rather looke to that we ſhould loſe in acquitting anye of our feaſt dayes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Whie what ſhould you loſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Our offerings, which are made much more aboundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on feſtiuall daies then vpon other. They ſaid alſo that there was of the Clergie many that liued very badlie, and marryeng not, yet kept they both women and children, euen aſwell and as openly as if they had wiues, wherevpon enſued much offence and ſlaunder among the people, wherefore they ſay it were better for them to marrie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:20"/>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Whie what ſhould you loſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Our offerings which are made much more aboundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on feſtiuall dayes then vpon other. They ſayd alſo that there was of the Cleargie many that liued very badly and marryeng not, yet kept they both women and children euen aſwell and as openly as if they had wiues, whervpon enſued much offence and ſlaunder among the people, wherfore they ſaye it were better for them to marrie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And what cauſe haue you to diſlike of that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>And haue we not cauſe of diſlike from freemen to bee made bondmen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>I rather thinke of ſlaues they would make you freemen, for tell me is there in the world any greater bondage or ſlauerie then vnto ſinne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Why then your ſelues reſting in ſinne with theſe your Queanes, do you not ſee that you are moſt ſhamefully the ſlaues of ſinne. And they diſcharge you of that ſlauerie, that ſeeke to haue you married, whereby you may liue honeſtlye with your lawfull wiues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>But doe not you ſee that if Clarkes ſhould marry, it would go ill with them, and that they ſhould loſe much of theyr authoritie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And doe not you thinke it much worſe, they ſhould be whoremongers, and thereby loſe more of their authoritie, if I might ſee Clarkes liue chaſtly, and that they would admit none to that dignitie, but ſuch as were at leaſt <hi>50.</hi> yeares of age, as God ſaue me I would thinke it better, they ſhould not marry. But among ſuch a number of young prieſts that take orders ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for couetouſneſſe then for the loue of God, in whom you ſee no ſigne of Chriſtian modeſtie, were it not much better for them to marrie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>But do you not ſee, that if Clarkes ſhould marry their children being not capable of inheritance, they ſhould either dye for want, or muſt be forced to become theeues, or their Fathers ſhould be compelled to rob the Church of her liuing, to beſtowe it on their Sonnes, whereby ſhould growe two great inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, the one that we ſhould encreaſe a number more of theeues and ſecondly that our Churches ſhould be diſpoiled.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:20"/>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Both theſe inconueniences may eaſily be remedied, if that you of the Clergie would labour to imitate the pouertie of them, whoſe ſucceſſors you pretend your ſelues to bee, and that you would not be aſhamed to bring vp your children in ſome ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt occupations, whereby they might get their liuing, and ſo ſhould they be alſo much better brought vp &amp; inſtructed in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith, whereby ſhould enſue much good to the publique weale, and ſo God helpe me it is a thing me thinks your ſelues ſhould deſire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Deſire quod you. God forbid that euer that ſhould come to paſſe, for marke ſir, whereto we ſhould then come, if I marrie I muſt then of neceſſitie liue with my wife, bee ſhe good or bad, foule or faire, all daies of my life or hir life: whereas now if ſhee that I keepe content me not to night, I can leaue hir to morrow and take an other. And beſides all this, if I liſt not to keepe a wench of mine owne, all the prittie wenches in the world are ours or to ſpeake more frankely and plainely, you keepe and mainteine them, and we enioy them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>But what becomes then of your Soules.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>O let that alone, for God is mercifull, I make my prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and confeſſe me to God when I lie downe, and when I riſe againe. I take no mans goods, I owe no man any money, I rob not by the high waies, I murther no man, I faſt all thoſe daies that the Church commaundeth, there paſſeth not a daye that I heere not maſſe, and doe you not thinke that all this is inough to make a man a Chriſtian, as for that other matter of women, to conclude we are men, and God is mercifull.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay truth, but ſurely heerin you are much leſſe then men, &amp; I ſtand in great doubt, whether God will be ſo mercifull as to pardon ſo many knaueries, if you perſeuere ſtill in them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Well we will leaue thoſe matters when we are older.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>You doe well to ieſt with God, but how are you aſſured to liue till the morrow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Be you not ſo ſuperſtitious, God hath pardon inough in ſtore, and ſee what you doe, would you haue the conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Churche broken, that hath continued ſo manye yeares?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And whye not? if ſo it bee conuenient for the publique weale of Chriſtendome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:21"/>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>And ſhall the Church then ſeeme to haue erred ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares together?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>You are much awrie in your accoumpt, for you ſhall ſee the church according to ſome one time dooth order things that in an other time againe it dooth annihilate. Doe you not reade in the Acts of the Apoſtles, that in the Councell of Ieruſalem it was ordred, that they ſhould eate no bloud nor ſtrangled beaſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yea I haue read it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Why therefore doe you not yet obſerue it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>I neuer ſet my wit on that place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then will I tell you, it was doone to ſatiſfie the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition of the Iewes, albeit the Apoſtels knew it was not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and therefore afterwards they derogated this conſtitution, as a thing ſuperſtitious: and yet it is not to be thought for this, that the Councell did erre. Then after the ſame manner, what inconueniences ſhould it be, if that which the Church in one time for vrgent reſpects had ordered, in an other ſhould be for reſpects more vrgent abrogated. And therefore me thinkes the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution ſhould now alſo be abrogated, and for truth I know no reaſon to the contrarie, but onely that your ſelfe alledgeth, it ſhould not be for your owne benefit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Well let vs leaue this now.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Now therefore do you not thinke that it ſhould be much better to redreſſe thoſe thinges which you ſaye the <hi>Almanes</hi> did require, and to amend your liues, and ſeeing we do honor you ſo much as the Miniſters of God, to be ſo indeed, and not to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in your hardneſſe, and ſo not to be the occaſion of great miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes as hath thereby happened.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>If the <hi>Almans</hi> deſire redreſſe in thoſe matters, the Church may prouide remedie when they ſee good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Well you ſee, that for aſmuch as you would not giue eare to the honeſt reprehenſions of <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> neither yet to the diſhoneſt rebukes of <hi>Luther,</hi> God ſought out an other kinde of meanes to conuert you, and therfore permitted thoſe Souldiers that ſacked <hi>Rome</hi> with <hi>Don Hugo,</hi> and alſo that the <hi>Colloneſi</hi> ſhould make that aſſault, whereof your ſelfe now complaine: for ſeeing that all were now become ſhameleſſe, and the behauiour and courſe of life they all held, he ſought to make them doe that for feare of looſing their liues, which for feare of deſtroying their
<pb facs="tcp:1927:21"/> ſoules, they would not do. And God, ſeeing that there was no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way left to deliuer his Children from perdition, he hath done with you euen as your ſelfe ſaid you would haue done with the Scholemaiſter of the Children which ſhould infect them with his vices, and would not amend.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>It may bee as you ſay, but what had the image com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted? what offences had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Reliques done? or the dignities, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honeſt and good people which were alſo robbed and ill intreated.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you report me the matter euen as it paſſed, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you were there preſent and I will tell you the cauſe as I thinke why God permitted euerie of thoſe thinges that yee ſhall trulie recompt vnto me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Great reaſon yee haue ſurely in all this that you haue ſaid, I ſhal with a verie good will do that you haue required: and heare whatſoeuer you wil ſay with a much better. You are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to know that the Emperours Armie hauing left their Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie at <hi>Sena,</hi> which was but a ſmall quantitie, with the greateſt ſpeed that euer was heard of marched euen to <hi>Rome,</hi> and arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued there the fifth of May.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>But what was the reaſon the Pope ſent not to require ſome communication.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Nay the good Duke of <hi>Burbone</hi> ſent to deſire of the Pope that he would ſend ſome perſon with whom he might treat vpon his entrance into <hi>Rome:</hi> But the Pope relying vppon his new league that he had made, and the Armie of the leaguers ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing promiſed to come to his ſuccors hee would not enter into any manner of communication: And when the Armie knew this, the very next day in the morning they reſolued to aſſault the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: And ſuch was our ill fortune, that euen at the beginning and within the Towne one with an Harquebuze happened to kill the good Duke of <hi>Burbone,</hi> whoſe death was the cauſe of much ill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Surely it euen breakes my hart to heare of ſo vnhappy a death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Our ſinnes was the cauſe, for if he had liued there had not bin ſo much miſchiefe done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Now would to God you had not had thoſe faultes, but who euer heard that the ſinnes of a Citie ſhould cauſe their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction that came to aſſaile them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>In this matter it may bee well ſaid, for the Duke of
<pb facs="tcp:1927:22"/> 
                  <hi>Burbone</hi> came not to conquere vs, but to defende vs from his owne armie, hee came not to ſacke vs, but to keepe vs that wee ſhould not be ſacked. It is wee that had moſt cauſe to lament his death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for himſelfe there is no man but rather doth enuy him then pitie him, for he loſt his life with the greateſt honor that euer did man, &amp; by his death atteined that, which a number of great Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains were neuer able to atteine, ſo that the verie memorie of him wilbe alwaies moſt honorable: onely one thing greeueth me, that is, the peril of his ſoule dying excommunicate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And why excommunicate?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe hee entred with an armed hand into the territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Church, and ſought to aſſaile the holy citie of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Do you know what one decree ſaith, to wit, that manie are excommunicate by the Pope, that are not excommunicate by God, neither doth the Pope entend, that he ſhould be excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicat that remaineth within the terrritories of the Church with intention to defend them, and in al that he can to prouide that they ſhould not receaue any damage as this Prince did.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yee ſay truth, neuertheleſſe his firſt motion was vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Of this your ſelfe before verie wel declared the cauſe, for hee was bound to defend the kingdome of Naples, beeing by the Emperor made his lieftenant generall for all Italie neither went he to poſſeſſe the landes of the Church, but to prohibite the Pope that he ſhould not poſſeſſe the landes &amp; territories of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and to bring him to ſome vnitie and concord with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Well let that be ſo, but to returne to our purpoſe. The Emperors armie was ſo deſirous to enter <hi>Rome,</hi> ſome to robbe and ſpoile, others for the extreame hatred they bare to that court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſome both for the one and the other cauſe, that the Spaniards and Italians on the one ſide by ſcale. And the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes on the other ſide by Pickaxes breaking downe the wall, entred by the Burge, on which ſide ſtands (as you know) the Church of Saint <hi>Peeter</hi> and the holy Pallace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Yea and a great manie of verie good houſes of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals. Of one thing I verie much maruell, that they within ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Artillerie, and thoſe without hauing none, how it was poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for them ſo eaſily to enter without the ſlaughter of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb facs="tcp:1927:22"/> onely of themſelues. But of you how many were ſlaine?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Sir you know how vncerteine reportes are alwaies in ſuch like matters. Some ſay Sixe thouſand men, but in truth there died not vpon the entrie aboue four thouſand, for imediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they retired themſelues into the Cittie, and I tell you truth I ſhould haue deemed this a verie great miracle, if afterwarde I had not ſeene the ſame ſouldiers haue done that they did, wherby I cannot beleeue that God would do ſo great a miracle for them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>You are much deceaued, for God did not this miracle for them, but to puniſh and correct you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Therein I beleeue you ſay the verie truth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>I woonder after their Generall was ſlaine, that they were not diſmaied (as commonly men are) and ſo did not leaue the fight.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>So was it ſurely but the death of this Generall infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them more and encreaſed their deſire to enter the citie with greater furie then before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Yee tell mee woonders.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Surely ſo it was, and this good duke of <hi>Burbone</hi> was ſo beleeued of all, that euerie man deſired himſelfe to die or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge the death of him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And therefore it was he me thinks that was cauſe of all that crueltie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>It is moſt likely to be ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lat.</speaker>
               <p>Oh mighty God how meruelous art thou in al thy works, &amp; in each perticular how wonderfully diſcouereſt thou thy power, thou determineſt that this good Duke ſhould bee killed, to the end that with the more rigor thy iuſtice ſhould bee executed: but let vs ſee where was the Pope all this while?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Euen in his owne Pallace, and ſo carleſſe, that it was a woonder hee was not taken, but ſeeing in how bad tearmes matters ſtood, hee retired himſelfe to the Caſtle of Saint <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelo</hi> with <hi>13.</hi> Cardinals and other Biſhops and principall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which ſtaied with him. And preſently the Ennemies entred and ſpoiled, and ſacked all that was in the Pallace, and the like did they in all the Cardinals houſes, and all other howſes, that were within the Burge, not ſparing anie, no not the Church of the Prince of the Apoſtles. This day they had there y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noughe to doo without entring into <hi>Rome,</hi> whither our
<pb facs="tcp:1927:23"/> people, hoiſing vp the draw Bridge, had retired and fortified themſelues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>But the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the reſt of you that were eſcaped when you ſaw this preſent daunger why did you not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord with the Emperour? what had you to do with the Popes warre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Surely verie little, but what would you haue vs to do? haue yee not heard the old prouer be that the lawes are as pleaſe the Prince. The Poore Romane people ſeeing their manifeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, would haue ſent Embaſſadors to the army of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour to haue agreed with him, and to haue auoided the ſacke, but the Pope by no meanes would conſent vnto it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>But herein tell the truth, for this was a ſtraunge inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie, had it not bin better for the poore people to haue taken any accord for their ſafetie, then to haue ſuffered that they haue done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay truth, but who would haue thought that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſhould haue falne out as they did. The Captains of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour preſently determined to aſſault the Cittie, and the verie ſame night fighting with their enemies they entred, and the ſack continued more then eight daies, in which time they had no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of nation, qualitie, or kinde of men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lat.</speaker>
               <p>O my God, and were not the Captaines able to remedie ſo great an euill?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Surely the Captaines did what they could, but all was in vaine, the Souldiers being ſo fleſht in theſe robberies as they were: you ſhould behold troops of Souldiers paſſing the ſtreets with cries, one carried priſoners, an other plate, an other howſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſtuffe. But the ſighes, groanes, and outcries of Women, and Children in all places were ſo pitteous, that my Bones yet ſhake to make report of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Yea and mine alſo to heare you tell of it: but they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried ſome reſpect to Biſhops and Cardinals?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>In truth no more then if they had bin ſoldiers as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and the like to the Churches and Monaſteries, all was fiſh that came to their nette, there was neuer ſeene more cruelty, leſſe humanitie nor feare of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>This outrage mee thinkes ſhould bee done by the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:23"/>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>In good faith our Spaniards were not idle, but plaide their parte aſwell as any, and then the <hi>Italian</hi> pages for they were the firſt that ſet to their hand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>But you your ſelues what did you all that while.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>We had good leyſure to pare our Nailes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>But in good ſouth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>What would you we ſhould haue done, ſome fled, ſome were tane and raunſomed, and all of vs ſped vnluckely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>But you that were ranſomed, did they then ſuffer you to liue in peace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>No as God ſaue me, we were euen in as great perrill as before, till ſuch time as we had nothing leſt that they could ſpoile vs of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>But whereof then did you eate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>The mercy of God neuer failed, when we had no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridges we eate Hennes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And vpon faſting dayes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>What talke ye of faſting daies, thinke you Souldiers make any difference betweene faſting dayes and Soundaies. O curſed generation, for to tell you the truthe me thought it was a moſt wicked thing that they ſhould haue ſo ſmall regard of the commaundements of the Churche.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Doe not you your ſelues contemne the Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, and doe you maruell that the Souldiers regarde not the precepts of the Church. But which thinke you to be the greater fault, ſimple fornication, or to eate fleſh in the holy time of Lent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>This is a gentle queſtion, the one is a naturall and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane matter, and the other a great abhomination, to eate fleſh in the holy Lent, O Ieſus ſpeake not of ſuch a thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Now as God helpe me, you haue a gallant iudgement, and do you not know that a man may better eate fleſh in Lent or on any other faſting day, then commit a ſingle fornication.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>And why ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe it ſhould be more wholſome for the body, and leſſe hurtfull for the ſoule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>And how ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Is it not cleere that fleſh is more wholſome then fiſh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:24"/>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then is it not more wholſome for the bodie to eate fleſh then fiſhe? and concernng the ſoule, is it not a greater of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to breake the commaundements that God himſelfe hath giuen then theſe of the Churche?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes that is true.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then is the ſinne greater to commit fornication, which is prohibited <hi>Iure Diuino,</hi> then to eate fleſh in Lent, which was onely a conſtitution humane.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>I am content to confeſſe that you haue reaſon in this alſo, ſo as you would ſhew me the reaſon why we thinke it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly a greater offence to ſinne againſt conſtitutions humane, then againſt the diuine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>We will enter no further into this, leaſt we want time for the reſt, but let vs proſequute our purpoſe,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Let it be ſo, let vs leaue this for ſome other time, and tell me now what was the reaſon that the iuſt ſhould ſuffer for ſinners. It is likely that in <hi>Rome</hi> there was many good men, that neither were partakers of the vices, nor in fault for the wars and yet ſuffred ioyntly with the bad.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>The bad receiued puniſhment for their wickednes, and the good vexations in this world to attaine the greater glory in the next.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>At leaſt they ſhould haue had ſome reſpect vnto the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Almains,</hi> and other nations that were Vaſſals and ſeruants to the Emperour, but they ſacking the Spaniſh Church of <hi>S. Iames,</hi> and the houſe of <hi>Don Pedro de ſalmanca</hi> Embaſſadour of <hi>Don Ferdinando</hi> king of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> &amp; the houſe of <hi>Don Antonio de ſalmanca</hi> that now is Biſhop of <hi>Gurcenſe.</hi> They left neither houſe, Church, nor man, that was in <hi>Rome</hi> vnſackt or ranſomed, euen the Secretary <hi>Perez</hi> himſelfe, who was reſident at <hi>Rome</hi> in the behalfe of the Emperour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Euen in this alone yee might know it was a manifeſt iudgement of God, &amp; no humaine action, neither executed by the will or commaundement of the Emperor, ſeeing they tooke no regard, no not of his owne Subiects and ſeruants.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay trueth, but is it not a horrible thing, that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſhould ſell &amp; raunſome Chriſtians as thoſe ſouldiers did?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Yes ſurely, it is a horrible thing indeed, but it is ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon a matter among men of warre, as we haue no cauſe to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell
<pb facs="tcp:1927:24"/> at any thing they did there, where they were woont not onely to ſell and raunſome men, but euen their ſoules alſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>What their ſoules, and how ſoe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>That will I tell you, but in your eare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Why, there is no body heere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>I care not for that, come hither.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Euen ſo? now I vnderſtand you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And doe you not thinke I haue reaſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes ſurely and that very great, and now doe I knowe that God hath ſuffered this euen to the end that we ſhould haue knowledge of our error. But now to tell you of the other Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals that were in <hi>Rome,</hi> and could not together with the Pope eſcape into the Caſtell of <hi>S. Angelo:</hi> how they were tane, and ranſomed, and their perſons full ill fauouredly handled, being drawne by the ſtreetes of <hi>Rome</hi> bare legged, among thoſe Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, that it was the greateſt miſery in the world to ſee them, eſpecially when men remembred the Pompe wherein they were woont to go to the Pallace, and of the multitude of ſeruants that attended them when they paſſed by the Caſtell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Surely this was indeed a horrible thing, but yet you are to conſider that this was their owne ſeeking, ſeeing they conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Pope ſhould make warres vpon the Emperour, and then breaking the truce made with <hi>Don Hugo,</hi> ſuffered the ſame in the name of the Colledge to be violated, and the moſt horrible ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations to be committed that euer were heard of. And how could you thinke but God would chaſtice you for it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
               <p>But alas what could they do, if the Pope would haue it ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>After they had doone all their diligence to perſwade him, if they could not preuaile, or haue doone him any good, they might haue gotten them out of <hi>Rome,</hi> and not haue beene par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of ſo great wickedneſſe, ſeeing the gates ſtood open, know yee not, that <hi>Agentes, &amp; Conſentientes pari pena puniuntur?</hi> and aſwell perhaps their owne ſinnes on the other ſide deſerued it, if not aſke M. <hi>Paſquine.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>No no, I neede not aſke him, I know that aſwell as Maiſter <hi>Paſquine.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>If you know that, ye need not maruell at that you ſawe, but onely that God of his infinit bountie ſhould ſo long diſſemble and beare with them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:25"/>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>But what ſay you of the mockerie they made of them? An Almaine clothing himſelfe like a Cardinall went riding about <hi>Rome</hi> in his <hi>pontificalibus</hi> and a bottle of Wine on the pum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell of his Saddle. And then a <hi>Spaniard</hi> in the ſame manner with a Curtezan behind him, was it poſſible in the worlde to make a greater mockery.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>But let vs conſider whether it were not a greater ſhame and mockerie of the dignitie of a Cardinall, hauing taken his hat, to doe the workes of a Soulder or worſe: or for a Souldier to take a Cardinals hat to counterfet the Cardinall, though the one and the other be naught, yet can ye not deny me, but that the firſt is the worſt, yea and more preiudiciall to the ſea Apoſtolike.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>It is true, but for concluſion, the Cardinals are men, and cannot leaue to doe like men, but this other is to abandon all reuerence and obedience to ſuch as it is due, without which no commonweale can ſtand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And with that would we be well contented, that the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals were men, and did not many times ſhew themſelues worſe then men. But tell me I praye you the Apoſtles were they not men too?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, but they were vpholden by the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And let vs ſee the holy Ghoſt that is now, is it not the very ſame that was then.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And if they would deſire it ſhould it be denied them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Noe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Why doe they not then requeſt it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe they haue not doone it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Theirs then is the fault, as you may ſee, and from henſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth they may know how great an abhomination it is, that they being the pillers of the Church, haue doone woorkes much worſe then Souldiers, and yet you thinke it a more abhominable mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for Souldiers to weare their habits. But why doe you tell me nothing of the Biſhops.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Why would you haue me tell you of them, they were handled euen as others, I will tell you that I ſaw among many honourable perſons that they had taken and carried to the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket place to be ſold, the Almaines led a Biſhop of their owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which ſtood vpon election to haue beene Cardinall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:25"/>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>What, to be ſold?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>And what maruell, yea euen with a bough in his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, as they do when they ſell beaſtes, and when they could find none to buye them, they plaied for them at dice, what thinke you of this geere?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Verie ill: and yet I tell you this is not without a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterye. Tell mee which eſteeme you more a Soule, or a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>A Soule without compariſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>But howe many Soules then haue you ſold in this world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Why how is it poſſible to ſell Soules?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Haue you not read in the Apocalips that they counted the Soules among their other Marchaundiſe. He that ſelleth a-Biſhoprick, hee that ſelleth a Benefice with cure of Soules, doth not hee ſell the Soules of his Subiectes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Surely you ſay moſt true, theſe thinges I neuer liked of, neither of giuing benefices to pencion with condition of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption at ſo much in the hundred, which is nothing elſe but to goe about to deceaue God Almightie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>In good faith was this their trick to deceaue, and in this maner? how many ſoules haue you ſeene playd at dice?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Infinite.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Now do you ſee, or hereby you may ſee and know your error, and need not meruell that thoſe ſoldiers that haue accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to liue by robberie ſhould ſell Prieſtes, ſeeing your ſelues ſold benefices, neither yet if they ſold Biſhops ſeeing your ſelues ſold Biſhopricks, and the one is ſo much more grieuous then the other as the Soule is more pretious then the Bodie: but rather you ſhould allow wel of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeeing they ſould neuer a Cardinal.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Was it not ynough that they did raunſome them, and made compoſition for their houſes and all they had in <hi>Rome,</hi> that nothing remained free.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Your ſelues will not remember thoſe purſes of ours that you haue emptied with your compoſitions, and therfore merueile you not if they alſo forget yours. Haue yee not read in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calips. Reſtore vnto her euen as ſhe hath rendred vnto you, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble their dublinges according to their woorkes, euen in the pot they haue mingled for you mixe them duble, euen ſo much as they
<pb facs="tcp:1927:26"/> haue glorified and delighted themſelues, ſo much giue them in tormentes and ſorrow, becauſe God is ſtrong that hath iudged her. What thinke you, are not theſe the verie iudgementes of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>My verie fleſh doth tremble in hearing of it: But I pray you tell mee, wherefore or to what purpoſe ſerueth the loſſe and ſpoile of ſo much money, as it is ſaid the ſacke of <hi>Rome</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted vnto by ranſomes and compoſitions aboue <hi>15.</hi> millions of Ducades.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>What call you this ſpoile and loſſe? in good faith I count it rather gaine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>And why gaine?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe for theſe manie yeares all the money of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome went to <hi>Rome,</hi> where it was conſumed and loſt, but now it is diuerted and found elſewhere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>And which way?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>The money it gat by pleas, by garboiles, by brables, by benefices, by penſions, by ſpoiles, by firſt fruites, by Buls, by indulgences, by confeſſionaries, by compoſitions, by diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, by excommunications, by curſes, by fulminations, by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauations and redagrauations, by connonizations, &amp; ſuch like exactions, the Souldiers haue taken as huſbandmen and labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers to ſowe round about the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Oh blacke laborrers that ſerued to deſtroy <hi>Rome</hi> in ſuch ſort, as it will not turne to bee <hi>Rome</hi> againe theſe <hi>500.</hi> yeares.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>O would to God that were ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>What?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>That <hi>Rome</hi> would not turne againe to thoſe vices it had, nor that therein ſhould raine no more ſo ſmall charitie, and loue and feare of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>But what had the ſacred pallace merited, and thoſe Chambers and painted haules, that was the moſt lamentable ſight in the World to ſee them made ſtables for horſes and all thinges in them vtterly defaced.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>In deed ſir you ſay well, and great reaſon it were that the whole Cittie ſuffering ſacke and ſpoile, that place ſhould be preſerued, from whence all the ill councell proceeded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>But then the Prince of the Apoſtles Church, and all
<pb facs="tcp:1927:26"/> the other Temples, Churches and Monaſteries of <hi>Rome,</hi> who is able to recount how they were handled and raunſacked, ſo as there remained in them neither Gold nor ſiluer, nor other thing of valiew, but all was by thoſe Souldiers robbed and ſpoiled, &amp; is it poſſible that God can like that his owne Churches ſhould be ſo handled and ranſacked, and thinges to his honor dedicated, ſo robbed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Surely ſir this is a thing indeed ſo ſoule and wicked, as it cannot be but condemned of any. Neuertheleſſe if yee looke well into it, yee ſhall finde euen in theſe thinges that haue bin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to the ſeruice of God ſo much ſuperſtition, &amp; the people therein ſo much abuſed, that I meruell not if God haue permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this and much more to the end ther may be in thoſe matters ſome moderation. The Marchant thinkes after hee hath gotten together an infinite quantitie of money, that all the ill hee hath done or ſhall doo ſhall be forgiuen him. If he build a church or a Monaſterie, or giue a Lampe or a Challice to a Church: and in this alſo do they deceaue, that they ſeeme to giue that for Gods ſake, which is rather for the moſt part giuen for a certaine pride, or for a certaine worldly vaine glory, as is manifeſt by the armes that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly euery one putteth on the things they giue, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their truſt in theſe thinges they thinke that now they neede no longer liue like Chriſtians, and albeit this bee an extreame errour, yet are they not aſhamed to admit it, ſo as thereby they make there profit by it, not conſidering in the meane time the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie they do to Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>And why an iniurie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lattan.</speaker>
               <p>Do you not thinke it an iniurie, yea and a verie great iniurie, that we being Chriſtians and inſtructed from God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhould be ignorant of that knowledge, which manie Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens onely by the light of naturall reaſon had attained of God. For they had atteined to this knowledge, that it was no true ſeruice of God to offer him any corruptible thing. They had at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined, that vnto a bodileſſe ſubſtance ſuch as God is, we ought not to offer anie bodilie thing for a principall offer, nor as a thing that ſhould bee verie gratefull vnto him. They ſaid that ſuch knew not what thing God was, that ſuppoſed hee tooke pleaſure in the poſſeſſion of ſuch thinges which many wiſe and
<pb facs="tcp:1927:27"/> good men thought a commendation in themſelues to eſteeme li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle as Iewels and Ritches: And yet wee Chriſtians are ſo blind as wee thinke our God is greatly ſerued with theſe corrupt and corporall matters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>By this meanes you would haue men do no ſeruice to God, neither in building of Churches nor in offering Challeces, and ſuch other ornaments.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>I ſay he doth better and more true ſeruice to God which fitteth his ſoule with ſuch vertues as God commaundeth to the end he may come and dwell in him, then he that buildeth a church, yea though it were made of gold, and as great as that of <hi>Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> for God to dwell in, when in the meane time by vices hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth God a ſtranger to his owne ſoule, albeit his intention therin were the beſt euen in the world: &amp; I ſay that it is a verie great error to thinke that wee pleaſe God by offring Gold or Siluer when it is done with an intention to be praiſed for it, or for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vaine reſpect. And I ſay that God is better ſerued if in ſteed of that wee giue vnto Churches which are but dead Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, wee did beſtow the ſame on the poore to relieue their neceſſities, ſeeing wee knowe they are the liuing Temples of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>By this reaſon wee ſhould haue neither Churches nor any other ornaments to ſerue God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>What ſhould wee haue no Churches? Yes ſurely I thinke wee ſhould haue manie more Churches, for hauing many good Chriſtians moe: of theſe any two or three being ioined to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in his name ſhould bee a Church, yea and beſides that, although the lewde would not build Churches or Monaſteries, thinke you that there would want good Men to doo it? But let vs behold this vniuerſall World, is it any thing elſe then a beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Church, wherein God dwelleth? What is the Sunne but a Lampe lighted to ſhine vnto the Miniſters of the Churche? What is the Moone? What bee the Starres, but Candles which burne in this Church of God. Would you your ſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire another Church? Doth not the Apoſtle ſaie, the Temple of God is holy, which you your ſelues are, would you haue other Candles to lighten this church, you haue the ſpirit, you haue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, you haue reaſon, and do you not thinke that theſe be good Candels?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:27"/>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes but yet no man ſees them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And you, haue you ſeene God? Behold brother ſeeing God is indeed inuiſible he wil be principally honored with things inuiſible, God will not be paid or contented with gold nor with ſiluer, neither ſtandeth in any need of theſe like things, ſeeing hee is Lord of all, he ſeeketh nothing but harts. Will you ſee this, Seeing God is omnipotent, If he would, could he not in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment make an hundred thouſand temples more ſumptuous and more ritche then the temple of <hi>Solomon?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes that is cleere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you what ſeruice ſhould you do him then, in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that he hath alreadie, and not yeelding that vnto him which he requireth. Let vs ſee if God delight in Temples, if God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in gold, if God delight in ſiluer, why dooth he not take all, ſince all is his.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Marry ſir, becauſe he would haue vs of our owne good wils, to offer it, to the ende we might that way haue meane to merrit?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>What merrit is it to giue vnto God that he leaſt eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, when ye will not render that he requireth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Now I perceaue you would not haue vs reteine the Churches we haue, nor that they ſhould take ornaments.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>I ſay I would not haue theſe things doone for vaine glorie, neither would I that to honour a Church of ſtones, wee ſhould leaue to honor the Church of God which is our ſoule, I would not, that to build an altar, we ſhould forbeare to ſuccour a poore bodie, or to repaire tables or dead images, we ſhould leaue the poore naked, which be the liuely images of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would I that we ſhould lay ſo great a foundation on thoſe things which we are not in any dutye bound to doe, neither yet that we ſhould giue men to vnderſtand, that the Lord is ſerued and pleaſed with the poſſeſſion of theſe things, that euery wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man contemneth and holdeth a praiſe in himſelfe, not to eſteeme. Tell me, whye did Ieſus Chriſt contemne all the ritches and wealth of this world?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe we ſhould likewiſe by his example valew it as nothing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Why then do we ſeeke to preſent vnto him theſe things, as matters very pretious and gratefull, ſeeing himſelfe we know
<pb facs="tcp:1927:28"/> contemned them, and would alſo that we ſhould contemne them, and not rather take care to preſent our mindes and ſoules pure and cleere from all vices and ſinnes, this being the moſt pretious and acceptable offering that we can preſent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>I muſe who ſhould teach you ſo many arguments be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yet ſo young.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then behold ſir it hath pleaſed God therefore to ſuffer theſe churches to be thus robbed, that we might euidently know that he eſteemeth as nothing all ſuch things as may be robbed, neither yet dooth he eſteeme any thing corruptible, to the end that heereafter we may rather preſent vnto him liuing then dead temples, And that we ſhould offer vp vnto him hartes and wils before gold and ſiluer, and that we ſerue him with ſuch things as he commaundeth, rather then with ſuch vanitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yea tell mee a thing that I neuer heard of, but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is ſo, tell mee howe and wherewith wee ought to ſerue him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>This is an other matter a part, whereof we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre an other tune more at our good leiſure, but nowe I praye you proceed on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Euen as you will, but what will you ſaye, that the very temples where God was woont to be ſerued and honoured, were become ſtables for Horſſes, what a thing was it to ſee the verye Church of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> both on the one ſide and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, all full of Horſes, euen to thinke of it, it breakes my harte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Certainelye, it was a thing that no good man could like of, and yet many times we ſee, that neceſſitie cauſeth things that by the lawe is prohibited, and in time of warre theſe and farre woorſe matters are commonly doone, whereof they are in fault that are the cauſe of the warre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>This is a gentle excuſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And why not, and doe you not alſo thinke that hee that draweth a greater and woorſe filthineſſe then that, into a place more holy then that, dooth hee not commit a greater abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>This is cleere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then tell mee if you haue read the holy Scripture, haue yee not founde in it, that God dwelleth not in Temples
<pb facs="tcp:1927:28"/> builded with the handes of men, and that euery man is that tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wherein God dwelleth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes ſometimes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then tell me which ſhould be the greater ill and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homination to make a ſtable of thoſe Temples of ſtone, where the Apoſtle ſaith God dwelleth not, or to make it of our ſoules, which are the true temples of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>This is cleere, that of our ſoules were the woorſe, but how can that be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Demaunde you howe, whye what call you a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>A place where Beaſts reſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>But what call you Beaſts?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Brute Beaſts without reaſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And are not vices brute and voide of reaſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes without doubt, and much woorſe then brute beaſts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Thus is it manifeſt, that it is farre greater abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to bring vices that are much woorſe then brute Beaſts, into the Soule which is the true Temple where God dwelleth, then to bring horſes into a Church of ſtone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Surely I thinke that true.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Heereby may you now knowe, how blinde your vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding was in <hi>Rome,</hi> that meeting daily by the ſtreetes, men that manifeſtly had their ſoules the ſtables of vices, of that you made no accoumpt, and becauſe you ſawe in caſe of neceſſitie, horſſes in the Church of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> you thought it an horrible abhomination, and broke your hart to thinke on it, And yet your harte was neuer broken, to ſee ſuch multitude of Soules full of ſuch filthie and abhominable ſinnes, and God by whome they were made and redeemed, baniſhed out of them, ſurely your reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is a gentle religion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>You haue great reaſon, but yet conſider I praye you, that which Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſpake, that God dwelleth not in Temples made with handes of men, was to be vnderſtanded of that time, wherein he ſpake it, for ſince and now in our Temples the Sacrament abideth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay truth, but haue not you confeſſed vnto me that vices are woorſe then beaſts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:29"/>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yea and ſo I ſay ſtill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Why then, he that bringeth into the Church a heard of vices that are worſe then Beaſts, is hee not worſe then he that bringeth into the church a troope of Horſſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>It ſeemes ſo to me, but theſe beaſts are inuiſible.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>What? will you ſay that God cannot ſee mens vices.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes God can ſee them, but men cannot, but theſe horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes we may all ſee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>By this reaſon ye would make it a leſſe abhomination to offend God then men, and then yee would excuſe the offence committed in appearing before God, ſo burdened with wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, becauſe men ſee it not, you aggrauate greatly the putting of Horſes into the Church, in that time of neceſſitie, becauſe they are viſible vnto men. But marke ſir I pray you, God is not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with the bad ſauors wherewith men are offended, The Soule wherein vices are rooted, that is it wherewith God is offended, and therefore hee requireth that this ſoule bee moſt cleere of vices and ſinnes, and many times he hath ſo commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs. And therefore yee take all things the wrong way: ye take great care to keepe neate and cleane the materiall Temples, and the true Temple of God which is your ſoules, you keepe it ſo full of vices and abhominable ſinnes, that they neither ſee God, nor know what thing he is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Now as God ſaue me you haue the greateſt reaſon in the world, but if you had ſeene the Souldiers how they carried along the ſtreetes, the poore Nunnes taken out of their mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, and other Virgins taken out of their Fathers houſes you would haue had the greateſt compaſſion in the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>This is a matter ſo common among Souldiers and men of warre, that albeit in mine opinion, it be indeed much more greeuous then all the reſt ioyned together, we make ſcarſlie any accoumpt of it, as if it were not worſe to defile a Virgin, which is the liuing temple, where Ieſus Chriſt dwelleth, then a church of ſtone or wood, wherefore the fault heereof muſt not onely bee laid to the charge of thoſe Souldiers, but much more vnto you, who began and raiſed this warre, and were the cauſe that they haue done that they did: verelye if the warre were cauſe of no other ill then this, euen for this alone you ought to leaue it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>The Regiſters and Records of the Apoſtolike Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb facs="tcp:1927:29"/> of the Buls and ſupplications, and thoſe of the Notaries and proceſſe are all deſtroied and defaced.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lattan.</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe I thinke ſurely God did permit, that toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with vice wee ſhould giue ouer all ſutes and pleas for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Eccleſiaſticall. For ſeeing theſe benefices are exequuted by Clarks, and the firſt &amp; chiefe charter of a Clarke ſhould be chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, how doth he hold charity that goeth to ſute with his neighbor?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>And why not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe that charitie is of that nature, that if it met with any of theſe ſuites, it would rather looſe the benefice then ſtand in controuerſie with his neighbor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>This were verie perfection.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lattan.</speaker>
               <p>And ſo ſhould all the Clergie bee men of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>All men cannot attaine to this perfection, but I pray you whereupon ſhould ſo manie Auditors, Proctors, Aduocats, regiſters, and other officers feed, if there were no ſutes &amp; pleas?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lat.</speaker>
               <p>Let them be Tailors, Waterbearers and Cowkeepers, and not defrawd vs vtterly of all Chriſtian charitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>And this is a gentle charitie of yours that ſo honorable perſons ſhould take ſo baſe occupations, but I pray you what ſhould we do with the ſutes alreadie commenced?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Let the benefice be beſtowed on the moſt worthy of them that are in ſute for it, or taken from them both, and giuen to a more worthie, and that could deſerue it better.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>By this meanes we ſhould haue no Iuſtice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Yes much more Iuſtice, for benefices ſhould be beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed on ſuch perſons, as ſhould do that they were ordeined for.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>And now do they not their duties?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>No ſurely, for theſe benefices are the goods of the poore, and while you waſt them in brables among Proctors and Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, the poore die for want.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Ye haue manie indeed that ſpend their liuings that way and ſome much woorſe, as your ſelfe I know can be a good wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. But whom would you haue to be the Iudge of the ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or inſufficiency of Clarkes to giue or take from them their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Euerie Biſhop in his owne Dioces, ſo as they would better examine and know the perſons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:30"/>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Well, but yee haue many Biſhops that haue not lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ynough, nor knowledge to do this.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And therein is there another ſinne committed, for ſuch ſhould not be admitted to be Biſhops, but other perſons therto deputed that were able.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Will yee haue me tell you the truth, euen that way too all would goe by fauour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Thinke not ſo there are a number of wiſe Biſhops and men of good conſcience, and others would follow their example. And in trueth I thinke this would bee the beſt remedie till there be ſome other more perfect reformation in the Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>And for pleas that are vppon ſeculer matters, what would you haue done?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>If I were a Prince I would either deuide it betweene them, or giue it all to the woorthieſt and honeſteſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Do you not ſee that hereby you would peruert and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow all Iuſtice?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lattan.</speaker>
               <p>Will you haue me tell you my minde plainely, God created all thinges for the vſe and ſeruice of man, but the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration thereof rather to one man then an other, becauſe they ſhould beſtow them where moſt neede was, and it is good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that ſuch as haue impart with ſuch as want. And it is good Iuſtice, that hee haue the adminiſtration of moſt, that beſt knowes how to vſe them, and contrarie manifeſt iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>By this meanes you would goe about to make a new world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>No, but I would eſtabliſh the good, and remooue the quite out of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>So long might I liue till you had gone through with ſuch an enterpriſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>God ſende the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> life, and then ſhall you ſee whether he will goe through withal.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>But tarrie, for yet haue yee not heard all. Neuer ſince the Emperours Armie entred <hi>Rome,</hi> till the time that I departed, which was the twelfth of Iune, there was not a Maſſe ſaid in <hi>Rome,</hi> nor all that time heard we a bell Ring, nor a Clocke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>The bad became little better by hearing of Maſſe when
<pb facs="tcp:1927:30"/> they did it without deuotion or reuerence, and the good would doo that in Spirite, which they coulde not doo with their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but how chaunceth the Prieſtes and Friers would ſaie no Maſſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>By God, and that is a gentle queſtion. Did not I tell you at the beginning there was not a Prieſt or Frier in <hi>Rome</hi> that durſt ſhew himſelfe in other garmentes then ſuch of a Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers as I were?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And why ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe the Almanes ſo ſoone as they ſaw a Frier, or a Prieſt in the ſteetes they would giue the woord and crie out, a Pope, a Pope, kill, kill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>As God ſhall helpe me I do now remember, that when I was in <hi>Rome,</hi> there were manie Propheſies that foretold of this perſequution of the Clergy, and that it ſhould be euen in this Emperours time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>That is indeed moſt true?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And why then would you not amend?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Why? who would then haue beleeued that it ſhould haue prooued true?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>That would any man that had well conſidered the ſtate of all thinges at <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Archd.</speaker>
               <p>But beſides all this, there was ſuch an extreame ſtinke in all the Churches, that no man could endure to tarrie in them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>A ſtinke and whereof?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>The Souldiers had opened many Sepultures hoping to haue found treaſure in them, but after they were opened they found nothing but the dead Carkaſſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Was it not much that you ſuffered of that perfume in telling of the money that yee exacted for burying of the dead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Now you are diſpoſed to ieſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>No in good faith but I tell you truth, that ſeeing you of the Clergie were not aſhamed to take tribute of the dead, a thing that euen among the Gentils was held moſt foule, as litle ſhould you haue lothed to haue entred to haue praied to God for them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Well you thought yee had done, but there remaineth yet woorſe matter for you to reſolue, for I haue kept the woorſt, and moſt grieuous for the laſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:31"/>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Well tell it me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>They left no Reliques vnſackt, and ſpared not to take the Gold and Siluer with their ſacrilegious handes, wherewith thoſe Reliques were couered, that it was the moſt horrible abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination in the world to ſee theſe Raſkals to enter thoſe places, whereunto Biſhops, yea Cardinals, yea the Popes themſelues ſcarſly durſt enter: And to take thoſe heads and armes of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and of the happie ſaintes, I cannot imagin what good could grow vnto Chriſtendome by ſuch an abhominable boldnes and contempt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Surely it was in deede a foule action, but I pray you tell me after they had taken the Gold and Siluer, what did they with the bones?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>The Almanes threw them downe, ſome in the Church yard, ſome in the holy Field, others drew them to the howſes of the Prince of <hi>Orenge</hi> and other Captaines, and the Spaniards as the people moſt religious drew them all to the houſe of <hi>Iohn de Vrbina.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>What, ſo diſpoiled?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>See what you doubt, I my ſelfe ſaw one baſketfull in the houſe of the ſame <hi>Iohn de Vrbina.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And do you take this for the moſt hainous?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>This is cleere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>But come hether, is not one bodie liuing woorth an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred dead?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then much more grieuous was the death of thoſe 4. thouſand men which you ſpeak of, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacke of theſe Reliques.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>And why ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe the Reliques are dead bodies, and the men were liuing, and your ſelfe haue alreadie acknowledged, that one ſuch is woorth an hundred of the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay true, but theſe were the bodies of holie men, and ſo were not the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>So much the woorſe, for the ſoules of theſe ſaints feele not the bad handling of their bodies, they being now in bliſſe: but theſe wicked ones dying in ſinne goe to hell, and ſo periſh both Soule and bodie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Archb.</speaker>
               <p>It is as you ſay, but neuertheleſſe it is an horrible
<pb facs="tcp:1927:31"/> thing that in our daies we ſhould ſee ſuch a bolde and outragious action.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Surely ſo it is, and yet is it not without cauſe, that God hath ſuffered it, for the deceipts were great that they vſed with theſe Reliques to beguile the ſimple people, and to get their money from them, for yee haue many Reliques that they will ſhew you in two or three ſeuerall places, as if you goe to <hi>Dura</hi> in <hi>Almanie,</hi> they will there ſhewe you the head of Saint <hi>Anne,</hi> the mother of our Ladye, and the very ſame they will ſhew you alſo at <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> So that manifeſt it is that one or both are falſe, vnleſſe they would haue vs beleeue alſo that our Ladie had two mothers, or Saint <hi>Anne</hi> two heads. And one or bothe theſe being counterfait, is it not a great wickedneſſe thus to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the people, and to worſhip a dead carkaſſe that perhaps was of ſome theefe hanged. But tell me which thinke you to be the greateſt inconuenience, either that we ſhould want the body of Saint <hi>Anne,</hi> or that vnder pretence of that relique, they ſhould make you worſhip the carkaſſe of ſome common wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Surely I had rather there ſhould neither be that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique nor any other, then that they ſhould make me worſhip a Sinner inſteed of a Saint.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Nay would you not rather that theſe bodies of Saint <hi>Anne,</hi> at <hi>Dura</hi> and <hi>Lyons,</hi> were put in a Sepulture and neuer ſhewed, then that ſo many people ſhould be abuſed by them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes ſurely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And of this ſort, yee had an infinite number of Reliques in the world, and little ſhould be our loſſe, if we had none of them at all, and would to God the inconueniences were ſo remedied. The foreſkin of our Sauiour cut off in circumciſion, I haue ſeene in <hi>Rome</hi> and in <hi>Burgos,</hi> and the very ſame they will ſhew you alſo at our Ladies Church in <hi>Antwerpe.</hi> Likewiſe the head of Saint <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> yee may ſee both in <hi>Rome</hi> and at <hi>Amians</hi> in <hi>Fraunce.</hi> But the Apoſtles if we will count them, albeit there were indeed but twelue, and one of them not to be found, and an other in the <hi>Indians,</hi> yet ſhall we find aboue 24. of them in our part of the world. The Nayles of the croſſe <hi>Euſebius</hi> writes were three, and one of them Saint <hi>Hellen</hi> the mother of the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> threw into the Adriatike ſea to aſſwage
<pb facs="tcp:1927:32"/> a tempeſt, an other ſhe cauſed to be caſt into an helmet for her Sonne, and of the third ſhe cauſed a bridle to be made for her horſe, and yet haue you in <hi>Rome</hi> one, and an other in <hi>Millaine,</hi> and an other in <hi>Coloine,</hi> and an other in <hi>Paris,</hi> and an other in <hi>Lyons,</hi> and I wot not how many elſewhere, Then for the croſſe, if all the peeces which they ſhew thereof through Chriſtendome, were gathered together, yee ſhould haue wood inough to lade a Charects. And of the teeth that Chriſt changed when he was a Child, euen in <hi>Fraunce</hi> alone ye haue at leaſt fiue hundred. Then of the milke of our Lady, of the heyre of <hi>Marie Magdelen,</hi> and the teeth of Saint <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi> there are reliques innumerable. And then euen of the vncertentie of theſe things, it is a great ſhame to ſee and heare what themſelues giue out to the people. My ſelfe laſt day in a very auncient Abbey was ſhewed a table of their Reliques, and there amongſt other things it named a peece of the Riuer of <hi>Cedron.</hi> I demaunded whether it were of the water or of the Stones of the Riuer, they tould mee I muſt not ieſt at their Reliques, an other was of the earth, wherevpon the Angel did appeare to the Shepheards, but I durſt not aſke them what they ment thereby. If I ſhould tell you of a number of their rediculous and impious things which they will tell they haue. As of the wing of Saint <hi>Gabriell,</hi> of the penitence of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Magdalen,</hi> the breath of the Mule and Oxe, of the ſhadow of the ſtaffe of Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> of the doublet of the Trinitie: a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of other things like to theſe. It were inough to make vs burſt with laughing. Onely I will tell you, how within theſe fewe dayes in a collegiall Church they ſhewed me a ribbe of the holye Sauiour, whether they haue anye other ſauiour then Ieſus Chriſte, or whether he left any ribbe heere behind them, let them looke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe things indeed, as you ſay, are rather to be laught at then lamented.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>You haue reaſon, and therefore I come to the other things which be vncertaine, yea and if they were certaine, yet are they ſtumbling blocks, to make a man commit Idolatrie, for they cauſe vs to hold them in ſo great reuerence, as euen in <hi>Aquiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grane,</hi> albeit they haue no other relique but a paire of olde bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which they ſay were S. <hi>Ioſephs,</hi> which they ſhew not but euery fiue yeeres once, there goeth thether an infinit number of
<pb facs="tcp:1927:32"/> people to behold them, as a thing diuine, and of theſe matters we make ſo great accoumpt, as if in one Church on the one ſide there ſtande in a ſhrine of Gold the ſlippers of ſaint <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi> and on the other ſide the holy Sacrament, the people will rather chooſe to go ſay their praiers before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſlippers of <hi>S. Chriſtopher</hi> then before the ſacrament, and this being ſo great a wickedneſſe, they doe not onely, not reprooue it, but moſt willingly admit and allow it, in reſpect of the great profit they gather by it, and the fine deuiſes they haue inuented for it. Let vs ſee then which were the greater inconuenience, either to haue no reliques at all in the world, or to haue men thus abuſed by them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot tell, neither would I trouble my head with theſe profound matters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And how profound, which thinke you of greateſt valew, either the ſoule of ſome ſimple bodie, or the body of a Saint.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>This is out of queſtion, that a ſoule is much better then a body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Why then what reaſon haue you (in ſeeking to honor the body of ſome ſaints, as they ſay, which perhaps notwithſtanding is the boddy of ſome theefe) to put in perrill ſo many ſoules?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay the trueth, and therefore may they very well thereof admoniſh the ignorant and ſimple ſort.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Very well, and yet euen theſe that ſhould admoniſh are many times themſelues ignorant, And yet beſides all this, why ſhould you put any one ſoule in danger without neceſſitie. Let vs ſee if you would in this Towne goe to our Ladies church of <hi>Prado,</hi> and knew not the waye, would you not thinke it a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye great inhumanity, if any man would direct you through the Riuer with greate daunger to drowne you therein, when you might more ſafelye and more quickelye haue gone ouer by the Bridge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes ſurely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And wherefore then do you ſeeke after Reliques?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe many times they ſtir me to deuotion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And deuotion to what end deſire you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>To ſalue my ſoule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Seeing then you may ſaue your Soule without perill of damning it, woulde you not rather chooſe the more ſafe waie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:33"/>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, and our confeſſors alſo ſay it is a ſinne for vs wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly to put our ſelues in danger to ſinne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>They ſay therein the very truth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>But yet what way haue you of greater ſafetie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>The ſame which Chriſt himſelfe taught, to loue God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all things, and to put in him our whole truſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay the truth. But becauſe I cannot do that, I go about to doe this other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>This is a great hereſie to ſay you cannot do it, deſire at leaſt of God grace to doe it. But if you will ſay you do requeſt it, and that God will not doe it, you make God a lyar, who ſaith, <hi>Aſke and you ſhall haue,</hi> And farther what a blindneſſe is this, doe you thinke to goe to heauen without fulfilling of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of God? albeit you haue an Arme of a Saint, or the peece of the Croſſe, or the whole Croſſe in your houſe, you may be an enemie to the croſſe, and doe you thinke to ſaue your ſelfe by the Croſſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Surely I was deceiued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then behold the common ſort haue ſo much more iuſt cauſe to complaine on them that lead them into theſe and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like ſuperſtitions, to put them in danger of their ſoules, then you of him that ſhould guide you through the riuer with danger to drowne you, as the ſoule is more worthie then the bodie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Well but yet the common ſort are more eaſilye by things viſible induced and directed to the inuiſible.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay truely, and therefore hath Ieſus Chriſt left vs his holye ſacrament of the Altar, and hauing this, I knowe not wherefore we haue need of any other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>And the true reliques indeed, would you not haue them kept and garniſhed with Gold and Siluer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>No ſurely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Wherefore.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Not to giue occaſion of ſuch another ſpoile, as this of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor yet to make men thinke, that the Saints are pleaſed to poſſeſſe theſe things, that thoſe which are good men do glory to contemne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay well, but doe you not ſee yet that the Saints may be offended with vs for taking away the Golde and ſiluer, wherein their bones be incloſed, and being ſo offended, may doe
<pb facs="tcp:1927:33"/> vs ſome hurt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>No, rather I thinke they would be verie well pleaſed to ſee thoſe thinges taken and imploied on the poore, who many times periſh for famin not hauing what to eate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>That vnderſtand not I vnleſſe you explaine your mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning better.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>I wil ſhew you plainly, that Saint which whileſt hee li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in this world, and had need of theſe goods, did neuertheleſſe leaue them and empart them to the poore for the loue of Chriſt Ieſu, do you not beleeue that much more he would be pleaſed, to haue the ſame done now after his death when he hath no cauſe at all to vſe them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes ſurely I think ſo, for wee that be no Saintes, yet when we die, and cannot carrie our goods with vs, wee are well pleaſed to giue them to the poore, and to deuide them among Churches and Monaſteries.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lattan.</speaker>
               <p>Why then tell mee wherefore ſhould you thinke a Saint ſhould bee greeued to haue that done with his goods now hee is dead, which himſelfe would haue done if he were aliue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>No ſurely I thinke a Saint would be verie wel plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſee that done with his goods now he is dead, which himſelfe would haue done if he were aliue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then you ſee plainly, that the Saintes who while they liued were ſo wel pleaſed to diſtribute their owne goods among the poore would now much more bee pleaſed to helpe the poore with that ſiluer and gold which good people haue preſented vnto them after they were dead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>So God ſaue me this reaſon is verie good, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue you ſay herein alſo the verie truth, and yet ſurely the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort would be offended.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lattan.</speaker>
               <p>No on my faith I dare aſſure you there would bee no offence taken, if it were prouided that ſuch ſuperſtitious people as regarded more theire Bellye, then the Glorie of Chriſt Ieſus ſhoulde not goe aboute to prouoke them to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Surely for this matter I hold my ſelfe fullie ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lattan.</speaker>
               <p>Thus you ſee how Ieſus Chriſt hath ſuffred that
<pb facs="tcp:1927:34"/> in <hi>Rome</hi> ſo greate a Sacke and ſpoile ſhould bee committed on Reliques, to remedie the dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iptes that were committed by them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Archde.</speaker>
               <p>Well, this I confeſſe, ſo as you will alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare vnto mee touching the ſmall reuerence vſed towardes the Images, what the reaſon ſhould bee that God would ſuffer that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>That I will tell you, neither will I denie that it was verie ill done, but God hath permitted it not without verie great cauſe, For you may ſee among the common people, yea, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen among many of the principall perſons alſo, that they did ſo muche repoſe themſelues vppon Images, and thinges viſible, that they had no care at all of the inuiſible. In my Countrey a verie good Man, a Deuine, going a viſitation of a Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke in the behalfe of the Biſhoppe, founde in one Church an Image of our Ladie, which they ſaide did manie Miracles, and was ſet ouer againſt an Altar of the Sacrament (in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof all Images in the Worlde are leſſe then nothing) And yet thereunto might you ſee them kneeling and knocking of their breaſtes before that Image of our Ladie. The good man when hee ſaw ſo great an Ignominie, as was thereby done to our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, conceiued ſo great a griefe as hee tooke away that Image and brake it into peeces. The people ſo much were mooued with this act, that they would haue kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him, but GOD deliuered him out of theire handes. The Clergie of that Churche beeing offended for theire rentes, that thereby they had loſt, trauelled with the people to complaine to the Biſhop, thinking he would preſently ſend to burne the poore viſitator. The Biſhoppe (like a wiſe Man) vnderſtanding the matter how it paſſed, reprooued the Viſitor of the contempt hee had committed in breaking the Image into peeces, but commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded much his act in remoouing it from that place, ſo that ſeeing there was ſo fewe ſuch good Viſitors in Chriſtendome, that would be agreeued with the diſhonour done to GOD, and to take away ſuch ſuperſtitious, God permitted theſe Souldiers to commit that ſpoile you ſpeake of, to the ende that leauing all ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition wee ſhould in ſuch ſorte honor Images, as wee do not diſhonor Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Archd.</speaker>
               <p>Surely this is a moſt Godlie conſideration and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:1927:34"/> I promiſe you, there is great need of remedie in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eſpecially in Italie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, euen here alſo aſwell as there: And if you will looke well into this matter, you ſhal ſee the verie ſame deceipts in Images that were in Reliques.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Archde.</speaker>
               <p>I knowe you ſaye truely, but I coulde tell you of another matter, that euen in thinking of it my fleſhe trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Tell it mee, and be not afraid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Can you imagine a greater wickedneſſe, then to breake open the Pixe of the Altar, and to let faule on the ground the holie Sacrament? Is it poſſible any good can come of this? Oh Chriſtian eares that can endure to heare it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Good God and haue you ſeene this too?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>No, but ſurely all men ſay it was ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>That which I haue heard was that a Souldier tooke the Pixe of Gold and left the ſacrament vppon the Altar, and did not throw it down on the ground as you ſay, but howſoeuer, it was a meruellous boldneſſe, and woorthie of great correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but in truth it is no new matter, but a thing that happeneth many times amonge Souldiers, and the fault is theirs which chooſe rather to liue in warre then in peace. But if it had neuer bin heard of before do you think this to be the greateſt abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that could be done? think you that it were not much woorſe to throw it into a dunghill?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>How? into a dunghill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lattan.</speaker>
               <p>I will tell you, but firſt tell mee which ſtinketh woorſt before GOD, a deade Dogge that lieth vpon a Doung hill, or a Soule that obſtinatelye continueth in his ſinnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>A Soule, for Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quod tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilius fetet, Canis putridus hominibus, quam anima pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catrix Deo.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then you will not deuie me that a ſinful ſoule is a foule filthie dunghill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>No ſurely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lattan.</speaker>
               <p>Seeing then a Prieſt that riſing in the Morning from his Queane (that I ſaye no woorſe) of courſe goeth to ſay Maſſe. A Prieſte, I ſaye, that holdes his Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice by Symmonye, and carrieth in his hart mortall rancor
<pb facs="tcp:1927:35"/> againſt his neighbour, that by right or wrong will heape vp rit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, becomming obſtinate in theſe and other vices, yea in much more woorſe then theſe goe euerie daie to receaue the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, do you not thinke that to let it fall in ſuch an one, is muche woorſe then to let it fall into a ſtinkinge Doung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>You talke to mee in a new language, I know not what to anſwere you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lattan.</speaker>
               <p>I meruell not though truth ſeeme to you a new lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage: But behold now how this is the cauſe that God hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered theſe things to be done, that Clarkes ſeeing how great ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homination it is to handle in this ſort the Bodie of Chriſt might thereby knowe and remember that themſelues haue handled it muche woorſe, that departing from their wicked manner of liuinge, they might clenſe their Soules from vices, and beautifye it with Vertues, that Chriſte might come to dwell in them, and not to keepe him as they doe, banniſhed from them:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Now as God ſaue me you haue verie well ſatiſfyed me in all my doubtes, and I was euen now meruelling to ſee how blinded all men were in theſe externall thinges without hauing regard to the internall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lattan.</speaker>
               <p>You haue verie great reaſon to meruell, for in verie truth it is a great pittie to ſee the falſe opinions wherein the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſorte are drowned, and howe backwarde wee are to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Chriſtians, and howe contrarie our woorkes are to the Doctrine of Chriſt Ieſus, and howe wee are burthened with Superſtitions, and in mine opinion all proceede from a peſtife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Auarice and peſtilent Ambition which at this time raigneth much more among Chriſtians, then in any other time: to what purpoſe do you thinke, do they perſwade the people that an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of Woode goeth to recouer Priſoners, and returnes all ſweating, but onelie to allure the ſimple ſort to make offeringes to that Image, to make thereof their owne profit, neither haue they anie feare of GOD in this ſorte to abuſe and deceaue the people, as thoughe our Ladie had no other meane to redeeme Priſoners, but to take with her a woodden Image. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be it, this bee a moſt ridiculous thinge, yet do the common people by reaſon of their authoritte beleeue it, and in this manner
<pb facs="tcp:1927:35"/> they make men alſo beleeue, that if they cauſe ſo many maſſes to be ſaid, with ſo many candles, at the ſecond ſorrow that you ſhall recouer that you haue loſt, O wretched ſinner, knoweſt thou not that in this ſuperſtition this cannot but bee a worke of the diuell, And were it not better thou ſhouldeſt looſe all that thou haſt in the world, then that thou ſhouldeſt introduce into a thing ſo holy, a thing ſo wicked. Euen of like accoumpt are theſe names, which you carry about your necks to eſcape death by fire, by water, and the handes of enemyes, enchantments and charmes made as the common people call them for men and beaſts, I cannot imagine how we came into ſo great a blindneſſe, that wee are falne into a manner of <hi>Gentillitie.</hi> He that will ſeeke to honour a Saint, ſhould trauaile to follow his holy vertue, but now in liewe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, wee chaſe Buls vpon his daye, beſides many other abuſes which are committed, we ſay and hold it a great deuotion, to kill foure Buls vpon <hi>S. Bartholmewes</hi> day, and if we kill them not, we are afraide that he will ſpoile our Vines, what greater gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitye can you wiſh then this? what is it leſſe to hould deuotion in killing foure Buls on his daie, then to ſacrifice foure Buls vnto <hi>S. Bartholmew?</hi> I doe not thinke it ill, that the people for recreation ſhould aſſemble, chaſe, and kill Buls on that day, but I thinke ſurelye that it is a wicked thing, to thinke that by ſuch acts we pleaſe God or his Saints: for in truth betweene killing of Buls with ſuch intent, and ſacrificing of Buls, I know no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference. Will you ſee another Heatheniſh cuſtome, as plaine as this, Behold how we haue deuided among our Saints euen the very ſame offices that the gods of <hi>Paynims</hi> had, inſteed of <hi>Mars</hi> we haue <hi>S. Iames</hi> and <hi>S. George.</hi> In liew of <hi>Neptune, S. Elmas.</hi> In liew of <hi>Bacchus, S. Martine.</hi> Inſteed of <hi>Aeolus, S. Barbola.</hi> in liew of <hi>Venus, Magedelena.</hi> The charge of <hi>Eſculapius</hi> we haue parted among many, <hi>S. Coſme,</hi> and <hi>S. Daman</hi> haue charge of common diſceaſes, <hi>S. Roque</hi> and <hi>S. Sebaſtian</hi> of the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, <hi>S. Lucie</hi> of the eyes, <hi>S. Polonya</hi> of the teeth, <hi>S. Aquida</hi> the Dugges, and of the other ſide <hi>S. Antony</hi> and <hi>S. Aloy</hi> of Beaſts, <hi>S. Simon</hi> &amp; <hi>Iudas</hi> of falſe witneſſes, and <hi>S. Blas</hi> of thoſe that neeſe, I knowe not to what end theſe inuentions ſerue, and this diſtribution of offices, but to make vs appeare altogether Paynims, &amp; to abandon the loue and truſt which in Chriſt alone we ought to repoſe, tormoiling our ſelues in ſeeking ſuch helpe
<pb facs="tcp:1927:36"/> of others, as he alone is able to giue vs, and thereof it alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that ſome thinke becauſe they recite a heape of Pſalmes, or a flocke of <hi>Roſarys:</hi> others becauſe they weare the habit of a <hi>Merced.</hi> Others becauſe they eate no fleſh on wenſdaies: others becauſe they are cloathed in Blew or yellow, that thereby they want nothing of perfect Chriſtians, reteining neuertheleſſe their enuie ſtill, their ranckor, their auarice, and their ambition, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vices, as entirely as if they had neuer heard what it is to a Chriſtian.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>And whence proceeds this as you thinke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Naye enter me not into this Laborinth, more perrilous I thinke then that of <hi>Creta,</hi> let that alone for an other daye, and tell me if in your opinion I haue accompliſhed as much as at the beginning I promiſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>I ſay you haue performed it ſo fully, that I hould all well emploied that I haue loſt in <hi>Rome,</hi> and all the troubles and trauailes I haue ſuſteined in this iourney, ſeeing I haue thereby gained ſuch a day as this, wherein me thinkes I haue ſhaken off from my ſelfe a peſtiferous cloude of abhominable blindneſſe and recouered the ſight of the eyes of my vnderſtanding, which I had loſt euer ſince I was borne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Seeing then you knowe this, giue thankes vnto God, and endeuour your ſelfe not to bee vngratefull for the ſame, and conſidering you remaine ſatiſfied of all doone there, it were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon you did alſo recount vnto me that which paſſed at <hi>Rome</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till your departure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>That ſhall I doe with a verye good will: you are to vnderſtand, that after the Armie entred into <hi>Rome,</hi> they placed a Guarde on the Caſtell, that none ſhould paſſe out nor in, and the Pope knowing the euident perrill he ſtood in, and the ſmall regarde thoſe Souldiers had of him he determined to take ſome compoſition with the Emperours Captaines, and therefore ſent to parle with <hi>Iohn Bartlemew de Gateuera,</hi> Regent of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> and gaue him certaine conditions, wherevpon he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to render himſelfe, to the end that on his parte he might offer them to the Captaines of the armie: and although that in going too &amp; to procure this agreement, he were ſhot throuh the Arme out of the Caſtell with an Harquebuze, yet before the end of fiue dayes after, the armie entred <hi>Rome,</hi> the capitulation
<pb facs="tcp:1927:36"/> was concluded and ſigned on either parte. Neuertheleſſe in this meane time the Pope receiuing news how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> armie of the legars came to aide him he would not haue that agreement executed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Now ſurely, this me thinks was one of the moſt wicked things of all, ye haue yet told me, had not poore <hi>Rome</hi> already ſuffered enough for his ſake, but that he muſt endeuour vtterlye to deſtroye it. If the Armie of the Legars ſhould come, it was to ſuccour him, it was cleere, they muſt fight with our Army, and thereby great ſlaughter muſt enſue on either ſide, if then ours did vanquiſh, the Pope and his partie ſhould fall into greater perill, but if theſe did conquere them, muſt Rome be new ſacked, why then had it not beene better to haue taken any accord, rather then hauing before ſeene ſo great miſchiefe, to be yet the cauſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more murders of people, and of a new deſtruction.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Surely you haue great reaſon, and much leſſe inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences had it been to haue accepted any conclution, then the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage that muſt haue enſued by he ſuccour of the Leagers. But ſo ſoone as the Emperours Armie knew of this, they preſentlye marched out of the Towne into the field, with reſolution to fight, But the Legars durſt not come of the Iſland, where they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained certaine dayes, and the Caſtell ſtill helde out, hoping on that ſuccour, or at leaſt that ſome diſcord might fall out in the Emperours Armie the Generall being dead. But they ceaſed not all this while to make their Mines and trenches to winne the Caſtell, yea albeit the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> that then remained the cheefe commaunder, were alſo hurt with a ſhot. Then came Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Collona,</hi> with the Lords <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> and <hi>Aſcaino Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonna,</hi> and they did remedie ſome parte of the euils that were committed. There came alſo the Viceroy of <hi>Naples,</hi> and <hi>Don Hugo di Moncada,</hi> and the Marqueſſe of <hi>Guaſto,</hi> and the Lord of <hi>Alorcan,</hi> and many other commaunders and Knights, with the Souldiers of the kingdome of <hi>Naples.</hi> And although in the meane time there ceaſed not ſhooting from the Caſtell, yet in the end the Pope vnderſtanding that the Legars armye returned, and that there was no hope to bee ſuccoured from them, hee accorded for to render vp the Caſtell into the Emperour his hands, with theſe conditions, that all the people within the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell ſhould goe freelye whether they woulde, not taking anye thing that was within the Caſtell, And for ranſome of theyr
<pb facs="tcp:1927:37"/> perſons and goods, the Pope promiſed to giue <hi>14.</hi> hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Duccats to pay the Souldiers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And howe ſo, was it not inoughe that they had robbed before?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes ſure it was enough, but that mought not be recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned any part of their paye. And for ſecuritie heereof, the Pope gaue them in pledge that good Creature <hi>Iohn Marte Gibber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Verona,</hi> with three other Biſhops, and <hi>Iacob Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limato,</hi> with other two Merchants of <hi>Florence.</hi> And beſides all this, conſented to leaue in the Emperours power, till ſuch time as they might knowe what his Maieſtie would commaund) the Caſtell <hi>Angelo</hi> and <hi>Oſtia,</hi> and <hi>Ciuita Vechia,</hi> with the hauen: and promiſed alſo to deliuer the Citties of <hi>Parma</hi> and <hi>Placentia</hi> and <hi>Modena,</hi> And his Holineſſe with the <hi>13.</hi> Cardinals that were in the Caſtell, went to the kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> euen from thence to go ſee the Emperour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Surelye this was a good meane to doe ſome good in Chriſtendome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>So was it, but to tell you the trueth, albeit they deſired it ſhould bee ſo reported (becauſe they thought it ill to hold the Pope and Colledge of Cardinals againſt their will) they ſayd it was their deſire, but in Concluſion they were gentill Priſoners.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>What ſay you then, that himſelfe deſired not to goe to <hi>Naples?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes but all this was but to make a vertue of neceſſitie, for ſeeing he ſought to ſtay ſo many daies in hope of ſuccour from the Legars, do you not thinke, that if he mought haue been at his owne choiſe, he would not haue beene rather in the Armye of the Legars, then where he now is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot deny vnto you, but it is very likely, but what can you tell if afterwards he changed his minde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Now certeinly I cannot tell, but I beleeue it not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe I thinke it well, that the head of the Church ſhould be handled in this manner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Let vs ſee then, is not a man that may auoyde miſchiefe bound to doe it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Who doubts that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Should not hee bee blame worthie, that ſhould giue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other cauſe to doe ill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:37"/>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>He ſhould be in the ſame fault, for <hi>Qui cauſam dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni dat, damnum dediſſe videtur:</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay verie well, then behold, the Pope either is there with his will, or againſt his will: if with his will, then is all well that you complaine of, but if againſt his will, then tell me wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would hee bee with the Armie of the Leagers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Why thats plaine to reuenge himſelfe of the inſolency and hurtes he had receaued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Let vs then ſee what would haue falne out.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>What could haue enſued but much diſcord, wars, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and damage through Chriſtendome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Then to auoid theſe ſo apparant miſchiefs, do you not thinke it better that hee ſhould bee in the power of the Emperor then elſwhere, albeit hee ſhould bee there againſt his will, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that we talked of before touching the Sunne that kept his Father tied: and if the Emperour would haue let him goe where himſelfe liſte, ſhould not the euilles haue beene iuſtlye imputed to the Emperor that would haue enſued, ſeeing hee gaue the cauſe thereof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>I confeſſe this too, but what will all both great &amp; ſmall ſay, but that the Emperour holdes the Pope and Cardinals pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>This will ignorant perſons ſay, whoſe iudgement it is impoſſible to ſatiſfie, whereas the wiſe and prudent knowing it to bee for the good of Chriſtendome, that the Pope ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in the power of the Emperour, will hold it, and account it verie wel done, and wil highly praiſe, the vertue and wiſedome of his Maieſtie, yea euen all Chriſtendome may thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues perpetuallie bounden for it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>As for mee I could bee well content that he ſhould bee whereſoeuer yee would haue him, ſo as they would giue me the poſſeſſion of my benefices, but I cannot tell whether you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how they ſtand excommunicate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And why ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe they haue apprehended and hold againſt his will the chiefe Paſtor of the Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Behold ſir hee ſtandes excommunicate that with a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked meaning wil not obey the Church. But hee that for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale of all Chriſtendome deteineth the people, and wil not
<pb facs="tcp:1927:38"/> let him loſe, onely to auoid the euils which would follow vppon his deliuery. Beleeue mee hee doth not onely ſtand not excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, but alſo meriteth much at Gods handes for it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Archd.</speaker>
               <p>Surely this is a thing verie likely and reaſonable, but I know not whether our Cannoniſts would graunt you this.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>That Cannoniſt that will not graunt this, ſhall ſhew himſelfe void of iudgement.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>I beleeue ſo too, but at one thing I was verie greatly diſpleaſed, that the Pope ſhould preſently giue pardon to all the Soldiers of all whatſoeuer they had done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And why are you agreeued at that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe they remaine all ritch and pardoned, and wee bewailing our loſſes and ſorrowes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Do you thinke that pardon of valiew? as much did hee to the <hi>Colloneſi,</hi> hee pardoned them firſt but after deſtroied them. A gentle kind of pardon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Archd.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot tell what I may beleeue, but that their ſoules were abſolued, and their purſes damned.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Why then did you not ſtand againſt it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, euen there about wee went to leaue our Skinne with our goods, thinges ſtood then in theſe tearmes, that you would pardon all paſt for that that was to come, if you had ſeene the Pope as I ſaw him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Where?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>In the Caſtle.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And why went you thether?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Ther were certaine benefices falne in my Countrey by the death of an neighbour of mine, and I went to demaund them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>An extraordinarie boldneſſe was this ſurely: Were you not aſhamed in ſuch a time to importune him with ſutes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>No ſurelie, for a ſhamefaſt man the Deuill will ſoone chaſe out of the Pallace, and manie more were there to begge them aſwell as I, and ſure I had as leeue preuent as bee preuented.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Well, I tell you againe, that moſt terrible is the Aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice of the Clergie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>A wonderous matter I promiſe you: and wherefore do you ſuppoſe, do wee of the Clergie come to <hi>Rome?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>I thought it had beene for deuotion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:38"/>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yes iwis, nowe ſurelye I was neuer in my life leſſe deuoute.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Nor yet leſſe a Chriſtian.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Well Sir, euen as it pleaſe you ſo let it be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>On my word, if I had beene Pope you ſhould not haue benefices onely for early riſing, ſeeing that after ſo notable a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequution, you had not left your couetouſneſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Yea euen for this is God very good, that he would not giue vs you, but <hi>Clement</hi> the <hi>7.</hi> who gaue it me preſently with a very good will, although I went in the habit of a Souldier as you ſee me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe I promiſe you this was euen an immeſurable clemencie, but tell me how found you him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>I found both him and all the reſt of the Cardinals and others about him, ſo ſad and ſorrowfull, that euen in beholding of them, the teares burſt out of mine eyes, He that had ſeene him goe in his triumphe with ſo many Cardinals, Biſhops, protono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries a foote, and himſelfe caried in a ſeat borne by men, beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon vs all his holy bleſſings, that he ſeemed euen a thing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine: and now to ſee him ſolitarye, ſad, afflicted, comfortleſſe, committed to a Caſtle, and that aboue all, is in the power and handes of his ennemies, and beſides all this, to ſee the Biſhops and other perſons Eccleſiaſticall that came to viſite him to be all in Souldiers apparell, and that euen in <hi>Rome</hi> the head of the Church ſhould not haue a man that durſt go in the habit of an ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall perſon: I know not what hart can bee ſo indurate, that hearing theſe things, ſhould not bee perſed with compaſſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Immeaſurable God how profound are thy iudgements? with how great clemencye doſt thou ſuffer vs? with howe great goodnes doſt thou call vs? with how great patience doſt thou tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vs? whilſt that we with the continuation of our ſinnes do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke againſt our ſelues euen the rigor of thy Iuſtice, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentlie both in the one and in the other doſt ſhewe vs thy mercie &amp; infinit goodnes, for all o Lord we yeeld thee infinit thanks kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing that thou doſt it not, but for our great good: for he that had ſeen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maieſty of that Roman court, ſuch and ſo great Cardinals &amp; Biſhops, ſuch and ſo many Cannons, Protonotaries, Abbets, Deacons, &amp; Archdeacons, ſo many Chamberleins, ſom ordinary, ſom extraordidary, ſo many Auditors, ſom of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chamber, &amp; others
<pb facs="tcp:1927:39"/> of the Chauncerie, ſo manie Secretaries, ſo many Scribes, ſome of Bulles, ſome of Writtes, ſo manie Abreuiators, ſo many Aduotates, Doctors, and Proctors, and a thouſand other kind of officers as were in that Court, and to haue ſeene them all come with that triumph and pompe to that Pallace, who would haue ſaid wee ſhould haue had ſuch and ſo ſudden a chaunge as this I haue now heard off. Now do I know that with the rigor of pain he doth recompence the delay of puniſhment.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Seeing alſo that in truth the Cardinals were faine to diſmiſſe their families becauſe they had nothing left to buy bread for them to feede vppon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Yet one thing doth comfort mee that at leaſt ſo long as they continue in this eſtate they ſhall the more liuelye repreſent thoſe they ſhould.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Who is that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Ieſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay truth, but in this caſe I had rather repreſent Pope <hi>Iulio</hi> with his triumphes, but tell mee I pray you how did the Emperour take theſe iniuries that in Rome his Armie had committed againſt the Church?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>I will tell you: immediatly after the certaine newes came of the euils that happened at <hi>Rome,</hi> the Emperour ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his compaſſion, cauſed the feaſts that were made for the birth of his Sonne <hi>Don Philip</hi> to ceaſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>And do you thinke that it greeued him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And what doe you thinke?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>Now ſurely I cannot tell, for on the one ſide I ſee things that ſhould diſpleaſe him, and on the other things that ſhould content him, and therefore doe I demaunde that queſtion of you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>And I will tell you, The Emperour is ſurely euen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a very good Chriſtian, and dooth ſo hold all his actions and accidents recommended and committed to the hands of God, as he taketh all chaunces in the beſt part, and therefore it comes, that wee neuer ſee him either in proſperitie ouermuch to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, or in aduerſitie to bee agreeued, So that by his vtter apparance, it is not poſſible for anye man to Iudge, but ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye I thinke, that in this, as in all other thinges hee will not leaue for to conforme himſelfe to that which ſhall pleaſe
<pb facs="tcp:1927:39"/> almightie GOD.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>But in good faith ſir, what thinke you now, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie will doe in a matter of ſo great importance as this, now in truthe he had need of very good councell, for if at this time he doe reforme the Churche (ſeeing now all men know what need there is beſides the ſeruice which he ſhould doe vnto God, he ſhall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine euen in the worlde the greateſt fame and glorye that euer Prince attained. And men will ſay euen to the ende of the world, that Ieſus Chriſt framed the Church, and the Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> which reſtored it, and if he doe not this, albeit all fell out againſt his will, and that he had or haue the beſt meaning in the world, it will not be poſſible to excuſe him, but that there will fall into mens mindes a very hard conceipt of him, neither doe I knowe what will be ſayd of him after he is dead, nor what accoumpt he can giue vnto God, for hauing omitted and not knowne how to haue vſed ſo notable and great an opportunitie as now he hath to doe vnto God, ſo notable a ſeruice, and ſo incomparable a good vnto the Vniuerſall commonweale of Chriſtendome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>The Emperour as I told and tell you, is indeed a very true Chriſtian, and very prudent, and hath about him perſons very wiſe in his Councell, I hope he will prouide for all to the glorye of God, and good of Chriſtendome. But ſeeing you aſke me this queſtion, I will not forbeare to tell you my opinion, and that is as touching the firſt. The Emperor ſhould.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porter.</speaker>
               <p>What nowe my maſters, the Churche was made to praye in, and not to prate in. Yee may goe foorth and pleaſe you for I will ſhut the doore.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Well Father we will away by and by.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porter.</speaker>
               <p>And you will not out I will lock you in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>That were a gentill peece of curteſie, but I thinke that Saint <hi>Frauncis</hi> hath giuen you noe ſuch commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porter.</speaker>
               <p>What care I for Saint <hi>Frauncis</hi> commannde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>I beleeue you well Father, let vs goe wee ſhall haue ſome other time to finiſh that is left.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>I would bee wounderfull glad to heare out that you began, but ſeeing it is thus, let vs goe a Gods name, vpon condition that we returne hether againe to morrow morning.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1927:40"/>
               <speaker>Latt.</speaker>
               <p>Nay let vs rather meete at Saint <hi>Bennits,</hi> leaſt this Friar turne vs out againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Arch.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay well Sir, let it be euen ſo, but in the meane time, Reade I pray you this Prayer in manner of a new <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> made by our Spaniards in couples that they ſoung euen vnder the window of our high Biſhop.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Padre nueſtro in quanto Papa,</l>
                  <l>Soys Clemeynte ſin que os quadre</l>
                  <l>Mas Rennego yo deel padre,</l>
                  <l>Que al bijo quita la Capa, &amp;c</l>
               </q>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1927:40"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
